<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Patriæ parricida, or, The history of the horrid conspiracy of Catiline against the commonwealth of Rome translated out of Salust, by C.C.</title>
            <title>Bellum Catilinae. English</title>
            <author>Sallust, 86-34 B.C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12375930</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12375930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 226:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Patriæ parricida, or, The history of the horrid conspiracy of Catiline against the commonwealth of Rome translated out of Salust, by C.C.</title>
                  <title>Bellum Catilinae. English</title>
                  <author>Sallust, 86-34 B.C.</author>
                  <author>Calle, Caleb.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 93 [i.e. 101], [1] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and F.C. for James Norris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Bellum Catilinae.</note>
                  <note>Running title: Patriæ parricida, or, Catiline's conspiracy.</note>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: Caleb Calle.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catiline, ca. 108-62 B.C.</term>
               <term>Rome --  History --  Conspiracy of Catiline, 65-62 B.C.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:60603:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut portrait of man</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CATILINE</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed for Iames Norris at the Kings armes without Temple Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Patriae Parricida:</hi> OR, THE HISTORY OF THE Horrid Conſpiracy OF CATILINE AGAINST The Commonwealth OF ROME.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>Saluſt,</hi> By <hi>C. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Plots, true or falſe, are neceſſary things</l>
               <l>To raiſe up Commonwealths, and ruine Kings.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Abſolom</hi> &amp; <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> and <hi>F. C.</hi> for <hi>James Norris,</hi> at the Kings-Arms without <hi>Temple-bar.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60603:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60603:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>JOHN FOWELL</hi> Bar. <hi>WILLIAM CARY</hi> Eſq; And <hi>JOHN GLANVILL</hi> Eſq; My Quondam Worthy School-fellows.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce Books (as well as Authors) want Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, under whoſe protection they may paſs free and undiſturb'd through the whole ſeries of Cenſure, nor be carpt at by every pretending <hi>Zoylus,</hi> and Factious Critick; the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring <hi>Catiline,</hi> dreſt in his
<pb facs="tcp:60603:3"/> Engliſh Garb, lies at your mercy for his Doom. He was once raging in his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and immoderate in his Ambition, affecting no leſs than the Soveraignty of the onely Empire of the World; but that ſame Civil War which he was the onely Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of, turn'd at laſt to his own ruine, like Envy in <hi>Ovid</hi> became his own Tormenter and Executioner: Or like that fooliſh Bird that ſtole a Coal from the Altar, which burnt and conſum'd he whole Neſt.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee to what Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and Precipices the <hi>Igni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60603:3"/> fatuus</hi> of his Ambition de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coy'd him. But 'tis not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fate of <hi>Catiline,</hi> but all, whoſe ſhallow brains enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch extravagant Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maera's, and are pufft up with the empty bubble of haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ambition; and 'tis the rareſt thing in nature, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they at laſt compaſs what they aim at, though to the attaining but the leaſt part of it, they render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the moſt contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Mankind. <hi>Catiline,</hi> who could content himſelf with no leſs Power than that of <hi>Sylla,</hi> yet condeſcended to be a publick Pander to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb facs="tcp:60603:4"/> Whores and Horſes for the Roman Gentlemen, whoſe Heads and Purſes he made uſe of, and whoſe Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines he caus'd as well as his own.</p>
            <p>The firſt ambitious men in the World, the old Giants, are ſaid to have made an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical attempt of ſcaling Heaven in ſpight of the Gods, and they caſt <hi>Oſſa</hi> on <hi>Olympus,</hi> and <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa,</hi> two or three Mountains more they thought would make them abſolute Maſters of Heaven, as well as Earth, but the Thunder came and ſpoil'd all, when they were
<pb facs="tcp:60603:4"/> come to the third ſtory.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The great Attempt was all in vain;</l>
               <l>They reapt their labour for their pain.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwel,</hi> the great Giant of our Nation, one of their Off-ſpring, when from an inconſiderable Captain he made himſelf Lieutenant-General of a little Army of <hi>Titans,</hi> which was his firſt Mountain; afterwards Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, which was his ſecond; and then abſolute Tyrant of three Kingdoms, which was his third; is really believ'd to have died of Diſcontent, becauſe he could not attain the name of King, and the
<pb facs="tcp:60603:5"/> formality of a Crown: But if he had compaſs'd that, yet ſtill ſomething elſe had been neceſſary to compleat his Felicity; either the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of an Emperour, or a God.</p>
            <p>And to this day what are the minds of many men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with, but the ſame Diſeaſe? what mean elſe theſe Plots and Conſpiracies (of which <hi>Catiline</hi> is but the Model)? and theſe flyings from Juſtice, but the curſed fruits of Ambition? What makes men of profligate Lives and loſt Conſciences endeavour the Death and
<pb facs="tcp:60603:5"/> Ruine of their own Monarch and the beſt of Princes? a Prince whom Wonders and an inſcrutable Providence have preſerv'd, and attended from his Cradle to his Crown; whoſe Grace has warm'd into life the Vipers that would have ſtung him, and entertain'd the croaking Vermine into his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
            <p>We might well now reflect on the Iron Age of <hi>Ovid,</hi> 
               <q>Filius ante Diem Patrios inquirit in annos:</q> Or the days of <hi>Sylla,</hi> when the Sword had free ſway, and
<pb facs="tcp:60603:6"/> acted what it pleaſed, and was as familiar with Entrails as the <hi>Augurs.</hi> And may not we as well imagine that <hi>Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> or <hi>Cethegus</hi> is now rais'd from the dead, and like <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi>'s Pidgeon inſpires men with the horrid principles of Bloud and Rebellion? What puts the Nation into Frights and Jealouſies, what ruines Friendſhip and Commerce among men, and turns the whole courſe of Nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chaos and Confuſion, but Ambition and its pernicious Attendants?</p>
            <p>Thus have I made ſo large a digreſſion in an Eſſay of
<pb facs="tcp:60603:6"/> Ambition: all that I have to ſay is, That Gratitude and a ſenſe of Honour for my Country-men and School-fellows, was the onely cauſe (in this interval of my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) why I were ſo ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to attempt ſo difficult a Task. The Original in Latin we learnt at School; and I know ſome will object, that like a School-boy I have handl'd it: but as I co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet not their Smiles, ſo I fear not their Anger, but am much of <hi>Martial</hi>'s humour, that only ſtudied to pleaſe and gratifie the Nobility;
<q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60603:7"/>
                  <l>Let Poetaſters beat their Brains</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe the Vulgar, what's their gains?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But my ambition was onely to pleaſe my ſelf, and if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, gratifie my Friends; (but eſpecially you, who are my Holy-day Friends, and ought to be diſtinguiſh'd from Pretenders): If I have done this, my ambition is at its height; and 'tis but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I ſhould ſtudy not only to requite, but if poſſible, erect ſo laſting a Monument, <hi>Quod nec Jovis ira, nec ignis</hi> ſhould be ever able to demoliſh
<pb facs="tcp:60603:7"/> their Names, who have ſo largely and generouſly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd me, and I doubt not but will continue it.</p>
            <p>I paſs by your Vertues and your Pedigree, and hate to be thought guilty of the leaſt of flattery: for as I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you my Friends, I ſhould be far from being ſo, ſhould I in the leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it. If Vertue be Nobility (as the Satyriſt obſerves) you have a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Claim to it: Vertue to a Noble Extraction adds Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre, carrying a Majeſty with it, and claiming a veneration from every one, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:60603:8"/> when conſpicuous in ſuch young Perſonages. Which that it may ſtill flouriſh, as it is the Wiſh of all that love you, ſo of none more, than,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and obliged Servant, <hi>CALEB CALLE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60603:8"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cius Sergius Catiline</hi> was ſprung from an Illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and endow'd with a vaſt ſtrength both of Mind and Body, but of as wicked and villanous a diſpoſition: to him, even from his youth, Civil Wars, Bloud, Rapine, and Diſſentions, were ever grateful and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and in them did he altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his Youth. He had a Body that could endure Hunger, Heat, and Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, almoſt beyond belief: His Mind was bold, ſubtile, various, that could counterfeit or diſſemble any thing; greedy of anothers Eſtate, and very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of his own; raging in his Paſſions, and <hi>more Eloquent than Wiſe:</hi> His De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60603:9"/> were of ſo vaſt an extent, that they immoderately coveted things incredibly beyond his ability. As ſoon as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of L.<note n="*" place="margin">A Noble Roman of the Families of the <hi>Scipio</hi>'s: He firſt ſerv'd under <hi>Marius;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards aſpiring to the power of a <hi>Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> became a great Enemy to <hi>Marius,</hi> and at laſt his ruine. Then had he power to over-rule all <hi>Rome,</hi> which he did by cutting off his Foes, and inriching his friends. At laſt he di'd at <hi>Puteoli</hi> of the Louſie Diſcaſe, (<hi>a ſit death for all ſuch aſpiring <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers,</hi>) after he had ſlain 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>000 men, 90 <hi>Senators,</hi> 15 of the <hi>Conſular dignity,</hi> and 2000 Gentlemen. Of his Life, <hi>vid. Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sylla</hi> had its <hi>Exit,</hi> an ex-travagant deſire ſeiz'd him of inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Commonwealth; neither did he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver value by what means he attain'd it, ſo he got the Reins of Soveraignty into his own hands. Still the wants of his Family and the guilt of his Villany more and more blow'd up the Coals of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content in his turbulent breaſt, beſides the corrupt Manners of the City; which Luxury, Avarice, and other complicated Debaucheries, never ceaſed to foment. Nor can I omit (the matter it ſelf requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it) to repeat and treat of the Acts and Inſtitutions of our Forefathers, both
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60603:9"/> in Peace and War; by what means they founded the Commonwealth, in what a proſperous condition they left it, and how <hi>Rome,</hi> from the moſt flouriſhing and beſt of Cities, became the moſt wicked and debaucht.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Trojans</hi> (I have read) were the firſt that built and inhabited the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> who like Vagabonds wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd from place to place under one<note n="*" place="margin">The Son of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Anchiſes,</hi> who when <hi>Troy</hi> was taken, came into <hi>Italy.</hi> He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Reign over the <hi>Latins</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chole</hi>) about the year of the World 279. at which time <hi>Sampſon</hi> was Judge of <hi>Iſrael. Ante urb. Cond.</hi> 427.</note> 
               <hi>Aeneas</hi> their <hi>Commander,</hi> to-ge-ther with the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaſi ſine Origine,</hi> by reaſon of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity; <hi>Vel Aberrigines, ex aberrando,</hi> a wandering People, whoſe Off-ſpring is not known.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borigenes,</hi> a brutiſh kind of People, without Laws, without Government, free and abſolute. 'Tis almoſt incredible to relate how both theſe, of a different Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, different Language, and different Manners, did ſo eaſily mix and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as ſoon as they were ſettl'd in one place; and afterwards when the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60603:10"/> of their Citizens, the goodneſs of their Manners, and the extent of their Territories, had advanc'd their fortunes, their Condition ſeem'd very proſperous, and their power formidable.</p>
            <p>But 'tis a general Maxime, that <hi>the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all things begets Envy:</hi> for we find that the bordering Kings and People began to wage War againſt them. Some few of their Friends came to their aſſiſtance, others out of fear and cowardize ſhun d all dangers; but the <hi>Romans</hi> were very active to incourage and exhort one another to incounter their Enemies, and with their Arms defend their <hi>Liberty, their Country, and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> But as ſoon as their Valour had diſpell'd the Miſt of Danger, they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſent Aids and Supplies to their Friends and Confederates, and <hi>became more belov'd by giving than by receiving of Favours;</hi> inſomuch that their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully-acquir'd Power obtain'd at length the Royal name of Empire.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60603:10"/>
            <p>They had * <hi>Delicti</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates,<note place="margin">A Deligendo: No ſitter term for it in Engliſh than <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates.</hi>
               </note> men choſen out to conſult the good of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> whoſe bodies as age had render'd weak and infirm, ſo their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was the more ſtrong and valid: To theſe, either in regard of their years or Office, they gave the honourable appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as ſoon as the City had aſſum'd its Liberty (ſo much did the deſire of Glory inflame them, that) 'tis incredible to relate in how ſhort a time, to how great an height they arriv'd.</p>
            <p>For the Roman Youth, as ſoon as they were capable, learn'd in their Tents Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Diſcipline by labour and practice, and took greater delight in ſhining Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and warlike Horſes, than in the ſordid pleaſures of Banquets and obſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities: And by this means it came to paſs, that nothing they undertook was ſtrange, or unuſual to them; no place, though never ſo difficult, impaſſable; no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60603:11"/> armed Enemy in the leaſt formidable; but a true Valour ſubdued and made e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing eaſie.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt emulation of Glory was among themſelves; for every one ſtrove to give the firſt onſet to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who ſhould firſt ſcale a Wall, or do the moſt noble action: this they accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their greateſt Treaſure, their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Fame, and the moſt honourable No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. They were ever covetous of Praiſe, and liberal of their Mony, and affected a great deal of Glory and a competent Eſtate. I could tell ye in what places the Roman Valour with a ſmall Party has conquer'd vaſt Armies of their Enemies, what Cities arm'd both by <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> they have beſieg'd and took; if I ſhould not make too great a digreſſion.</p>
            <p>The Atchievements of the <hi>Athenians</hi> were indeed very great and magnificent, but ſomewhat leſs and obſcure than what Fame has reported them; but becauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60603:11"/> 
               <hi>Athens</hi> abounded with ſuch great and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Writers, their Actions were ſo <hi>hyperbolically</hi> celebrated, and their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour had as great an <hi>Encomium,</hi> as the beſt Wits of the Age could expreſs in words.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Romans</hi> had never that <hi>Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> becauſe every of the moſt prudent and ſage men, were ever employ'd in the moſt weighty Affairs; and no one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them exercis'd the Gifts of the Mind without thoſe of the Body: the<note n="*" place="margin">Eſſe quàm videri bonus malibat. <hi>ſic Aeſchilus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> beſt men knew <hi>that Vertue conſiſted in Action,</hi> and were more addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to do, than talk; and had rather their good deeds ſhould be commended by others, than that they themſelves ſhould be Trumpets to ſound forth their own Praiſe. Every where, both at home and abroad, <hi>good Manners</hi> were their onely ſtudy: Joyn'd with the greateſt <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> and the leaſt <hi>Self-intereſt,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Vid. D. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de Civit. Dei, lib. 2. cap. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Goodneſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60603:12"/> and Honeſty more prevailed with them by the Law of Nature, than of Nations:</hi> Their Enemies were the onely Objects of their Wrath, Hatred, and Diſcontents; and the onely Strife among themſelves was, how one Citizen ſhould out do another in works of Vertue; in their Devotions to the Gods they were liberal; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimonious at home, and very true and faithful to their Friends: They main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd themſelves and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth by theſe two Arts; in War, <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage;</hi> and in Peace, <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I have known puniſhment to be inflicted oftener on thoſe who contrary to command have fought againſt their Enemies, and though call'd home, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but unwillingly, than on thoſe who have baſely deſerted their Colours, and given way to the Enemy. But in Peace they exercis'd their Authority more by Mildneſs than Severity, and had rather pardon and paſs by an Injury, than en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to revenge it. But when by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60603:12"/> Induſtry and Juſtice they had raiſed the <hi>Republick</hi> to its Grandeur, great (yet conquer'd) Kings, mighty Nations, and vaſt Multitudes, were ſubdued by the <hi>Roman</hi> Valour; and <hi>Carthage,</hi> that was emulouſly fir'd at the Glory of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire,</hi> lay buried in its own Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines; both Sea and Land lay open to them, and <hi>Fortune</hi> began to play mad freaks, and make a mixture of every thing: Thoſe who had undergone all Labours and dangerous Adverſities, left Riches and Idleneſs to be wiſht for by others, and accounted them as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den too heavy to be born.</p>
            <p>And therefore firſt an immoderate deſire of Riches, and then of Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo far increaſed, that they became the Subject and Original of all Miſchiefs: for <hi>Covetouſneſs having ſubverted Faith, Honeſty, and all good Arts, taught men Pride, Cruelty, Contempt of the Gods, and Bribery, and compelled the greateſt part of Mankind into Falſhood, to ſpeak one thing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60603:13"/> and think another, and to value Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip not for its own ſake, but for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that attended it; and to regard more the outward countenance of the Face, than the inward beauty of the Mind.</hi> Theſe things at firſt grew by degrees to an height, at length to be pleaded for and vindicated.</p>
            <p>Afterwards when this Contagion like a Peſtilence had infected the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Empire, which before was moſt juſt and excellent, was metamorphos'd into cruel and intolerable. At firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Ambition</hi> poſſeſs'd the minds of men more than Covetouſneſs, being the more plauſible Vice, and nearer reſembling Vertue: for the nature of the wiſe man and the ignorant are alike deſirous of Glory, Honour, and Command; but the one takes juſt and true meaſures, and the other (blinded with unlearned Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance) by unjuſt and deceitful Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies, endeavours to attain them. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs is no other than a ſtrict ſearch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60603:13"/> and a fixt deſire after Riches; <hi>which no wiſe man was ever guilty of,</hi> becauſe it has that poyſonous quality, to render both the Mind and Body weak and effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: 'tis infinite and unſatiable; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it poſſible for Plenty or Want to hinder or diminiſh it.</p>
            <p>But after the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>L. Sylla,</hi> his good beginnings were attended with far otherwiſe events: for the Army fell immediately to Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and Violence; one coveted this houſe, and another that field: neither had they any Conſcience or Modeſty, but made the poor Citizens the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Objects of their Cruelty and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</p>
            <p>Hence it came to paſs that <hi>L. Sylla,</hi> that he might the more endear the Army (he led into <hi>Aſia</hi>) to himſelf, gave it a tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for all Luxury and Debauchery: for the bewitching delicacies of the Place, and the pleaſures of Peace, ſoon turn'd the flinty breaſts of Souldiers into ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and effeminacy.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60603:14"/>
            <p>There was the fatal place where firſt the Roman Army grew to an habit of <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Intemperance;</hi> here they firſt came to admire painted Tables and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſs'd Cups, and privately and publickly to ſteal and plunder, rob Temples, and make no diſtinction at all between things ſacred and prophane; ſo that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they came and were victorious, they never left any thing for the conquer'd to enjoy.</p>
            <p>For proſperous Events are a great clog to the Spirits of wiſe men, leſt they too ſhould become Slaves to their own Victory; but when the richeſt men were accounted the moſt honourable, and that onely they were inveſted with Command and Authority, the edge of Valour was ſoon blunted, Poverty was accounted a Reproach, and Innocence a moroſe Ill-nature.</p>
            <p>So that Riches were the unhappy cauſe that Luxury, Avarice, and Pride, ſo generally invaded the whole <hi>Roman
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60603:14"/> Youth,</hi> that they were given up to Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and Prodigality; to be profuſe of their own Eſtates, and yet very covetous of anothers; to ſet no value either on Shame or Modeſty, but to mingle divine and humane things promiſcuouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</p>
            <p>It was a Golden time when whole Houſes and Villages, built after the forms of Cities, came to viſit the Temples of the Gods, founded by our moſt religious Anceſtors; when they adorn'd the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Gods with Piety and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their own houſes with Renown and Honour; when they never debarr'd the Conquered of any thing, but onely the liberty of doing Injuries.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, theſe (rather Bruits than Men) by the greateſt Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the height of Villany, (as if to do Injuries was onely to make uſe of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) have ſtript their Companions of all thoſe Priviledges that were left them by their moſt valiant Conquerors:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60603:15"/> For why ſhould I tell you things which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſeen are incredible, that many private men have levell'd Mountains, and drain'd Oceans, to whom their Riches ſeem'd as a Play-game, and though lawful enough in themſelves, yet were wilfully abus'd to all manner of Impiety.</p>
            <p>Neither did they reſt here, but no leſs immoderate deſire of Filthineſs and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and other unlawful Extravagancies, did poſſeſs them: even men chang'd the courſe of Nature, and acted the parts of women; and women did no leſs impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently proſtitute their ſhame in <hi>publick;</hi> both Sea and Land were ranſackt to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them Delicates <hi>to pleaſe the witty gluttony of a Meal;</hi> and they took greater delight in Sloth and Drowſineſs, than in a moderate Sleep and natural Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: No longer did they undergo Hunger, Thirſt, Cold, or Hardſhips, but made every thing ſubſervient to their Luxury.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, when their Prodigality
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60603:15"/> had brought their Eſtates to a low ebb, fir'd the <hi>Roman Youth</hi> to ſome raſh At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; for <hi>a mind once polluted,</hi> or tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>with debaucht principles, never wants fewel to maintain them:</hi> and therefore in every reſpect they gave Prodigality a greater ſcope, and a freer career.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Patriae Parricida: <hi>OR,</hi> CATILINE<hi>'s Conſpiracy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN ſo great and ſo debaucht a City, <hi>Catiline</hi> had every day <hi>Cabals</hi> of <hi>Penſioners</hi> for Miſchief and Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; for every <hi>Debauchee</hi> that had either by <hi>Riot, Gaming,</hi> or <hi>Whoring,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd his Patrimony, or had mortgag'd his Eſtate to procure a Pardon for ſome notorious Crime; beſides all <hi>Parricides, Sacrilegious, arraign'd at the Bar,</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60603:16"/> and fear'd it;</hi> beſides <hi>Thieves, perjur'd,</hi> and <hi>Murderers;</hi> and laſtly, all thoſe whom any <hi>notorious Villany, want,</hi> or an <hi>evil Conſcience</hi> had made infamous, were by <hi>Catiline</hi> pickt up as the fitteſt perſons for his purpoſe. Theſe were his very Family and Domeſticks; and if any one of an honeſt Reputation, free from thoſe Enormities, ever happen'd into his acquaintance, by perpetual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions and inſenſible Allurements, he becomes a <hi>Proſelyte</hi> as bad as the worſt. But for the moſt part he coveted the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of young men, becauſe their Spirits are more pliable in the bloom of their age, and conſequently ſwallow the Bait with leſs difficulty; therefore he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted a particular Temptation to every particular Conſtitution: To ſome he would become a Pander, for others he would procure Dogs and Horſes; and without regard either to Modeſty or Expence, he would never refuſe the moſt vile and abject ſervices, ſo he could but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60603:16"/> bring them over to his humour, and make them true to his intereſt.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Catiline,</hi> when but a Youth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſeveral notorious Rapes, firſt on a noble Virgin, then on a Veſtal <hi>Nun,</hi> and was guilty of many ſuch egregious inceſtuous Extravagancies, contrary to all Law and Nature. At laſt he ſell in love with <hi>Aurelia Oreſtilla,</hi> in whom no good man found any thing commendable but her Beauty; and becauſe ſhe doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to marry him, fearing her Son-in-law, then in age, 'tis really believed he poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd his onely Son, to make way for their unlawful Marriage; which thing in my opinion was the chiefeſt cauſe why <hi>Catiline</hi> ſo ſoon endeavour'd to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his Conſpiracy: <hi>For a mind polluted with Impiety, is hateful both to Gods and men, and can never be ſedate nor compos'd with ſleep nor watchings.</hi> Thus did ſelf-guilt weary and waſte his inraged, turbulent breaſt: from thence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded that languid bloudleſs colour in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60603:17"/> his face, ſtaring eyes, his pace confus'd, now quick and then ſlow; and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie diſcontent, and War within him, diſcover'd it ſelf too apparent in his looks and geſtures.</p>
            <p>But he not onely betray'd a great part of the <hi>Roman Youth,</hi> but he taught them divers <hi>Formula's</hi> and Methods in the commiſſion of notorious Villanies. Out of them he furniſhed himſelf with falſe Evidences and counterfeit Seals, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they Set all their Credit, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and Dangers at a very deſpicable value.</p>
            <p>But after he had made ſhipwrack of their Reputations, he ſoon commanded things of far greater conſequence: for if but a ſmall cauſe or opportunity for Miſchief did occur, leſt their hands ſhould grow dull for want of uſe, yet their minds ſhould be gratuitouſly miſchievous to circumvent and ruine the Innocent as well as guilty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catiline</hi> repoſing ſo great a truſt and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60603:17"/> confidence in theſe his Friends and Allies, (conſidering that there was no Country but to which he and they were deeply indebted, and that <hi>Sylla</hi>'s Souldiers were in want, who reflecting on their former Victories, wiſht once more an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for a Civil War) began to conſult by what means he might beſt curb the Commonwealth, and take the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into his own hands. In <hi>Italy</hi> there was no Standing-Army, and<note n="*" place="margin">Father-in-law to <hi>Julius Caſar,</hi> for his valour ſurnamed <hi>Magnus.</hi> He was of ſuch an Heroick Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that he could not admit of an Equal; and <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſo ſtout, that he could not endure a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour: whence aroſe the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cn. Pompeius</hi> was wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging War in the utmoſt confines of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, that he himſelf ſtood very fair for the <hi>Conſulate,</hi> and the <hi>Senate</hi> nothing at all cautious and ſuſpectful, but every thing mov'd in a ſafe and undiſturbed Sphere; all which wonderfully favour'd his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne. And to that purpoſe, about the<note n="†" place="margin">Which was about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Junei,</hi> for the <hi>Calends</hi> were the firſt day of every month. <hi>Vid. Godw. Antiq. Rom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Calends</hi> of <hi>June</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60603:18"/> he firſt began to diſcover it apart, to perſwade ſome, and allure others, and promiſe all, that the Aids and Forces he ſhould have (conſidering the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> was careleſs and unprovided) would make the rewards of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy great and anſwerable. When he had diſcovered what he thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, he ſummon'd all thoſe, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of whoſe wants afforded them the greateſt ſtock of Reſolution and Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Thither came of the Senatorian Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>P. Lentulus Sura, P. Antronius, L. Caſſius. C. Cethegus,</hi> the two <hi>Sylla's, P.</hi> and <hi>Serv. L. Vargunteius, Q. Annius, M. Porcius Lecca, L. Beſtia,</hi> and <hi>Q. Curius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the Equeſtrian Order (or Knights) came <hi>M. Fulvius Nobilior, L. Stanlius, P. Gabinius Capito, C. Cornelius,</hi> beſides many nobly deſcended out of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and free Towns. Many more Noblemen were made more privately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it; whom the deſire and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60603:18"/> hopes of Command, more than Want or Neceſſity, perſwaded to be Traytors. The reſt that favour'd the Deſigne were for the moſt part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility, who deſir'd to live in eaſe either ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly, or effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately; preferring<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic in bello Jugurthino.</hi> Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam opibus ſuis conſideret, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men non debere incerta pro cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis mutare. Irem <hi>Plautus, in Pſeud.</hi> Certa amittimus, dùm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certa petimus. Et <hi>Heſiodus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Chimaera's</hi> before Realities, and the dubious events of War, before the certain tranquillity of a ſettled Peace.</p>
            <p>At that time there were ſome that thought that <hi>M. Licinius Craſſus</hi> was not altogether ignorant of the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> becauſe he bore an inveterate hatred to <hi>Cn. Pompeius,</hi> who was then General of a great Army, and was very willing to raiſe any Forces whatſoever to curb his growing Greatneſs, hoping that if the Plot had took effect, to make himſelf Commander in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>When they were all met, <hi>Catiline,</hi> though he had diſcovered ſeveral things
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60603:19"/> before apart, yet thought that in this matter 'twas expedient to convene all, to give them a ſufficient ſatisfaction of the goodneſs and juſtice of his <hi>Cauſe;</hi> took them apart into a private Room, and thus beſpoke them.</p>
            <q rend="margSglQuotes">
               <p>In vain were all opportunities of time and place, and pregnant hopes of Dominion and Soveraignty, if either your Valour or Integrity were in the leaſt to be ſuſpected; neither would I through ignorance or a capricious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, leave a ſubſtance to embrace a ſhadow, or refuſe ſolid certainties to graſp empty hopes, or Clouds of Air: but ſince in many and prodigious diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties I have had ſufficient experience of your Courage and Honeſty, my mind prompts me on to undertake the greateſt and the moſt honourable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize imaginable: for I know what things will turn to the profit and diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of us all; and for you to <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Nill</hi> the ſame with me, is the very
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60603:19"/> height and complement of Friendſhip. What I now deſigne, you have been ſeverally acquainted with, how glorious and honourable our Undertaking is; but my Spirit is more inflam'd, when I reflect how miſerable the reſidue of our lives will be, unleſs by ſome noble At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt on the publick <hi>Liberty</hi> we endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to evade it.</p>
               <p>For as ſoon as the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was delivered to a few rich and powerful men, mighty Kings and Tetrarchs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their Tributaries, vaſt Multitudes and whole Nations became their Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and paid them Stipends; and we that are truly valiant, honeſt, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly born, have been rank'd with the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Vulgar, and been baſely ſubject to their humours, without any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or the leaſt mark of Greatneſs, to whom (were things juſtly manag'd) we ſhould appear great and formidable: for we ſee that all Command, Honour, and Riches, are abſolutely poſſeſs'd and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60603:20"/> diſpos'd of by them, when onely Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Diſgrace, and Poverty are all our fortunes; which how long (O invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Spirits) will ye undergo! Is it not much more honourable to die in the Bed of Honour in a Righteous Cauſe, than loſe a miſerable and a ſordid life in the baſe ſervice of a Great man's Pride? But now (O the faith of Gods and men!) Victory ſmiles, and ſeems ready to put her triumphant Palm into our hands; and what ſhould hinder? Is not the power in our hands? our Age in its full ſtrength and vigour? and our Courage equal to our Age? and every thing as it were conſpires to make us abſolutely happy? When on the contrary, to them, Age, Riches, and Security, render every thing old and tedious. <hi>Nothing now remains but the Attempt it ſelf.</hi> Other things the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of our <hi>Cauſe</hi> and the neceſſity of our Action will conſequently diſpatch: for what one of us, that hath the true
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60603:20"/> 
                  <hi>Roman</hi> bloud flowing within him, can endure that ſuch men ſhould have ſo great an affluence of Riches, even whole worlds of Treaſure, which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſely waſte in Riots and Exceſs, in levelling Mountains, and draining Seas; when we, who are far more meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and deſerving, cannot ſupply the neceſſitous wants of our ſelves and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: they are happy in the number of their Palaces, and we miſerable in the want of a ſmall Houſe, or a ſettl'd Habitation. They can purchaſe rich <hi>Attick</hi> Tables, carv'd Images, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſs'd Cups; pull down this new Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and raiſe another, and endeavour by all means imaginable to conſume and even torment their Treaſures, which are as boundleſs as their Paſſions; while we labour under the intolerable burden of Wants at home, Debts abroad, in a deplorable condition, and much more deplorable hopes: and therefore what ſhould hinder an immediate Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60603:21"/> Lo, <hi>Liberty, Liberty!</hi> the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs whom you oft have courted, now courts you, attended with that ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Dowry of Riches, Honour, and Renown. <hi>Fortune</hi> has deſign'd theſe Rewards onely for Conquerours; and now the Cauſe, Opportunity, Danger, Want, and all the ſplendid Spoils of glorious War, ſhould have a greater influence upon <hi>your</hi> Spirits, than an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Oration, though deckt with the choiceſt Flowers of pleaſing Rhetorick. Either uſe me as a Commander, or a Souldier; both my Preſence and my Courage ſhall ever attend you. Theſe things when I am <hi>Conſul,</hi> with your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and help, I hope to effect, unleſs perchance my Truſt fail me, and you more inclin'd to live ſlaviſhly, than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand victoriouſly.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Soon as the Conſpirators had heard this, though they had neither money nor probable hopes of carrying it on, yet they thought they ſhould reap ſufficient
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60603:21"/> ſatisfaction in diſturbing the Peace of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> and to that end they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd him to propoſe in what nature or condition the War ſhould be, what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, what hopes of Aid did ſeem to favour it. <hi>Catiline</hi> immediately promis'd them new Laws, the<note n="*" place="margin">They were properly ſaid to be proſcrib'd, whoſe Names were very fairly written and ſet up in the <hi>Forum</hi> (or Exchange) to give notice that for ſome Miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Goods were to be ſold, and the Malefactors baniſht.</note> Proſcription or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration of the rich mens Eſtates, their Magiſtracies, <hi>Church-lands,</hi> Plunder, and every thing which the will of the Conquerour ſhould lay claim to.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, <hi>Piſo</hi> was with an Army in the yonder <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>P. Sitius Nuceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in <hi>Mauritania</hi> with another; both his Friends, and both Partners in the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy: that <hi>C. Antonius,</hi> his familiar Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, a man every where ſurrounded with wants and neceſſities, endeavour'd the <hi>Conſulſhip,</hi> whom he hop'd ſhould be his Collegue; and as ſoon as he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd that, he would begin the Attempt.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60603:22"/> Soon as he had ſpoke this, he fell a rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on all the <hi>Loyal Party</hi> with oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious Language, and dire Imprecations; then naming every one of his own, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to praiſe them for the nobleneſs of the Undertaking; to one he objected his Poverty, to another his Ambition; many he advis'd of the danger and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace they ſhould contiue in without it: but moſtly he inſiſted on the Victory of <hi>Sylla,</hi> and the rich Spoils and Plunder that attended it. At length, when he perceived the joy of their hearts appear in their looks, deſiring them to conſider what he had recommended to them, he diſmiſs't the <hi>Conventicle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At that time there were ſome that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that <hi>Catiline,</hi> after he had made an Eloquent Oration to allure the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Miſchief to an Oath of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, gave each one a Cup of Wine mixt with<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hac de re Florus ſic ſcribit.</hi> Additum eſt pignus Conjurationis Sanguinis humanus, quem circumlatum pateris bibere. Summum Nefas, niſi amplius eſſet, propter quod biberunt.</note> 
               <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Bloud;</hi> which when (with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60603:22"/> an Execration, as is uſual in ſolemn Sacrifices) they had drunk off, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd every Circumſtance of his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Intrigue. And this they report he did, that, ſeeing they were ſcared with the horridneſs of the Plot, they might be the more faithful one to another, and keep the Deſigne more ſecure from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Aſſociation</hi> there was one <hi>Q. Curius</hi> of a Noble Family, but involv'd in all debaucht and villanous practices, whom the <hi>Cenſors</hi> baniſht the Senate for his ſcandalous deportment. This man as he was bold and daring, ſo he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foppiſh and idle; he could neither be ſecret in things imparted to him, nor ceaſe to be the Divulger of his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries, making no diſtinction at all between what he did or ſaid.</p>
            <p>Betwixt him and <hi>Fulvia,</hi> a Lady no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſcended, was contracted a very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate and immodeſt Familiarity; to whom when Poverty had render'd him
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60603:23"/> leſs acceptable, he immediately boaſted of and promis'd Golden Mountains, and I know not what impoſſibilities; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times threatning her with death if ſhe did not incline to his lawleſs humour; at length came to be more boldly rude than uſual.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Fulvia</hi> ſo prudently manag'd him, that by degrees ſhe got out of him the Cauſe of his inſolence, and thought that a matter of that dangerous conſequence to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> ought not to be longer kept private; inſomuch that many whom ſhe made acquainted with it, were very deſirous to intruſt the management of the Commonwealth to <hi>M. Tullius Cicero,</hi> whom before moſt of the Nobility en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd, and thought it a degradation to the <hi>Conſular dignity,</hi> that ſo great an honour ſhould be conferr'd on ſuch a new Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart perſon, though of extraordinary Parts and Abilities; but when dangers made things look with ſo ill an aſpect, that Envy and Pride ſuddenly vaniſht and gave place to Safety.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60603:23"/>
            <p>Therefore in the next <hi>Senate, M. Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Cicero</hi> and <hi>C. Antonius</hi> were declared<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic dicti, à Conſulendo Populo:</hi> No Citizen could be made <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul,</hi> till the forty third year of his age.</note> 
               <hi>Conſuls;</hi> which at firſt ſtruck the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators with a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> fear: Neither was the rage and madneſs of <hi>Catiline</hi> any whit abated, but urg'd him to greater and more fatal Reſolutions.</p>
            <p>For now he began to fortifie ſeveral of the moſt convenient and chiefeſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſent Money to <hi>Manlius</hi> at <hi>Faeſulae,</hi> which he had borrow'd both on his own and the account of his Friends. This <hi>Manlius</hi> became after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Head of the Rebellion.</p>
            <p>He betray'd likewiſe a vaſt number of all ſorts and conditions, beſides ſome women who had got vaſt Eſtates by the proſtitution of their bodies. Even theſe <hi>Catiline</hi> deſign'd to be inſtrumental to his <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> who by Courtſhip and other verbal Services, ſhould engage their Husbands to his intereſt, and if not, to kill them.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60603:24"/>
            <p>Amongſt theſe was the Lady <hi>Sempro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> a true <hi>Virago,</hi> who commonly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many notorious Miſchiefs with a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculine impudence. This woman was very nobly deſcended, and of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent beauty, very happy in a Noble Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and lovely Children, learn'd in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Tongues, could ſing and dance more<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Semproniam</hi> hic reprehendit <hi>Saluſtius,</hi> non quod ſaltare, ſed quod optimè ſcierit, quod ut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Notavit <hi>Aemilius Probus</hi> in <hi>Epaminondae</hi> vita.</note> ingeniouſly than an honeſt woman ought to do, and had ſeveral more qualifications ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to her wanton Luxury: ſhe accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any thing at an equal value with Vertue and Modeſty; and it would be very difficult to diſcern whether ſhe was more prodigal of her Money or her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; being ſo naturally laſcivious, that rather than not be courted, ſhe would court others.</p>
            <p>But this woman had before this made ſhipwrack of her Fame and Credit, was perjur'd, guilty of Murder, and involv'd
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60603:24"/> in all manner of Luxury and Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>But her Wit and Parts were not in the leaſt deſpicable; ſhe could compoſe Rhymes and Sonets, was very jocular in all Society, and could talk either mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, moderately, or laſciviouſly, and had indeed a great deal of <hi>Complaiſance</hi> and Gentility in her Converſation.</p>
            <p>Theſe things done, and the Plot ſo far laid, <hi>Catiline</hi> the enſuing year endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured no leſs vigorouſly for the <hi>Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> than before, hoping that if he was choſen, he ſhould manage <hi>C. Antonius,</hi> and caſt him in what mould he pleas'd.</p>
            <p>Neither was he now quiet, but ſought by all means poſſible to intrap <hi>Cicero,</hi> who was no leſs ſedulouſly cautious to prevent him: for from the beginning of his Conſulate he ſo manag'd <hi>Fulvia,</hi> that ſhe promis'd to induce <hi>Q. Curius</hi> to diſcover the whole Aſſociation. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he ſent away <hi>C. Antonius</hi> his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue to the Government of a <hi>Province,</hi> ſuſpecting leſt he alſo ſhould have ſome
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60603:25"/> private grudges againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; and had continually a private party of his Friends and Clients about him for the ſafeguard of his perſon.</p>
            <p>But when the <hi>Council</hi>-day came, and <hi>Catiline</hi> ſaw that none of his Deſignes and Stratagems againſt the <hi>Conſul</hi> took effect, reſolv'd immediately to take Arms and abſolutely try the utmoſt event of all things, ſince all his Contrivances met with a far different Event than he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
            <p>Upon this he diſpatched away <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> to <hi>Faeſulae,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Etru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria; Septimius</hi> to the Territories of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenum;</hi> and <hi>C. Julius</hi> into <hi>Apulia;</hi> ſome one way, and ſome another, as he thought convenient.</p>
            <p>In the mean time he himſelf was not idle at <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſtill plotted the ruine of the <hi>Conſul,</hi> to prepare fit Inſtruments and Materials for firing the City, and to beſet ſtrong and convenient places with armed men, to be himſelf armed, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60603:25"/> command and exhort others to be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and in readineſs for what they were to execute, to be active and vigilant both by night and day, and let no labour nor hardſhip in the leaſt weary nor diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them.</p>
            <p>But at laſt, when he ſaw nothing take effect, at an unſeaſonable time of night he ſummon'd the Chief of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy by <hi>M. Porcius Lecca,</hi> complaining of their ſloath and tardineſs in ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty an Affair. He gave them to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that he had ſent <hi>Manlius</hi> before to thoſe Forces which he had order'd to be in Arms, and others into other op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune places, to <hi>commence</hi> the War; and that he himſelf deſir'd to haſten to the Army, if by any means poſſible he could firſt kill <hi>Cicero,</hi> becauſe he was the chiefeſt hindrance and countermine to all his undertakings.</p>
            <p>At this they were all ſtartl'd, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dubious what the Event might be. At length <hi>C. Cornelius</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Knight,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60603:26"/> and <hi>L. Vargunteius</hi> a Senator, reſolv'd that very night or the next morning to take a few armed men, and go by way of viſit to ſalute <hi>Cicero,</hi> and ſo ſurprizing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to kill him at his own houſe.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Q. Qurius</hi> underſtood how great and imminent a danger threaten'd the <hi>Conſul,</hi> he immediately made <hi>Fulvia</hi> the happy Inſtrument of its diſcovery, inſomuch that when they came to the door, they were deny'd entrance; and for ſo great and noble an Exploit, had onely their labour for their pains.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Manlius</hi> rais'd the <hi>Rabble</hi> in <hi>Etruria,</hi> who were very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Reformation, becauſe their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Wants and Grievances brought to their remembrance, that in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Sylla</hi> their Eſtates were <hi>ſequeſtred,</hi> and their Goods <hi>confiſcated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides theſe, there were a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Banditi</hi> or Robbers (of which that Country abounded) and ſome of <hi>Sylla</hi>'s old Souldiers; though they had ſuch
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60603:26"/> rich Plunder and large Spoils, yet their Luſt and Luxury left them nothing to enjoy.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Cicero</hi> underſtood this, a dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fear preſently poſſeſs'd him, leſt the City could no longer be defended from their Treachery by a private Council. Neither was he ſufficiently ſatisfi'd how ſtrong the Army of <hi>Manlius</hi> was, nor what it immediately deſign'd to do, but makes the Senate acquainted with the whole matter, which was heighten'd and aggravated before by the Rumours of the common people.</p>
            <p>Upon this, the <hi>Senate</hi> immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed (as is uſual in matters of great conſequence) that it ſhould be the care of the <hi>Conſuls,</hi> what in them lay, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the Security of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and gave Commiſſions to the Magiſtracy to raiſe an Army, wage War, to engage Friends and Citizens, and to exerciſe full power and authority both abroad and at home.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60603:27"/>
            <p>Not long after, <hi>L. Senius</hi> (or <hi>Servius</hi>) read ſome Letters in the <hi>Senate,</hi> which he reported to come from <hi>Faeſulae;</hi> the Contents of which were, That <hi>Manlius</hi> was in the Field with a great Army, the 5th of the Calends of <hi>November:</hi> Some related ſeveral ominous Portents and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies; others, that there were ſeveral private Cabals and Conſults, how to ſend Arms to <hi>Capua,</hi> and raiſe a ſervile War in <hi>Apulia.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Senate</hi> decreed that <hi>Q. M. Rex,</hi> and <hi>Q. Metellus Creti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> ſhould be ſent, the one into <hi>Faeſulae,</hi> and the other into <hi>Apulia,</hi> and the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring places.</p>
            <p>But the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod praeirent Populo:</hi> That judg'd matters within the City, and had uſually places of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Army; the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at laſt came to ſixteen.</note> 
               <hi>Praetors Q. Pompeius Rufus,</hi> and <hi>Q. Metellus Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> were ſent the one into <hi>Capua,</hi> and the other to the Territories of <hi>Picenum,</hi> with orders to raiſe ſuch an Army as the time and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger did require.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the <hi>Senate</hi> decreed that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60603:27"/> large Rewards ſhould be given to any one that would make any diſcovery of the Conſpiracy, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To a Servant <hi>Freedom,</hi> and an hundred <hi>Seſterces;</hi> to a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Libertus:</hi> He or ſhe that had ſerv'd as an Apprentice, and was afterwards manumis'd, was call'd <hi>Libertus,</hi> or <hi>Liberta.</hi>
               </note> freed man a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred: They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed likewiſe, that the Companies of the <hi>Gladiators</hi> ſhould be drawn out and ſent into <hi>Capua,</hi> and other municipal places, as there ſhould be occaſion; and that continual Guards and Watches ſhould be ſet over the whole City, and ſome inferiour Magiſtrate ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them.</p>
            <p>Upon this the whole City was in a Conſternation, and every thing lookt with a far different Aſpect than before; for inſtead of their exceſſive Mirth and Wantonneſs, (the effects of Idleneſs) Sorrow and Grief invaded every one; Terrour and <hi>Panick</hi> Fear ſo diſorder'd them, that they would neither truſt to the ſafety of any place, nor the honeſty
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60603:28"/> of any man; they were ſo confus'd that they were unfit to make War, or live in Peace, meaſuring the greatneſs of their Danger by the greatneſs of their Fear.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the tender women, whom the unaccuſtomed fear of War had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, had regard to the greatneſs and glory of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> neither ceas'd they from being the Afflictors and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors of their own breaſts, and with up-lift hands to Heaven implor'd its mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on their poor Children. Often would they ask confuſed Queſtions, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at every ſhadow. Pride and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy were now no more, ſince they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted their own Country, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>cruel</hi> and inraged breaſt of <hi>Catiline</hi> ſtill perſiſted in the carrying on of his Villanies, notwithſtanding ſuch ſtrong Watches were ſet every where. To diſſemble his Hypocriſie, and excuſe himſelf as if juſtly provok'd, he came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Senate;</hi> Then <hi>M. Tullius Cicero,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60603:28"/> either ſtartl'd with fear at his preſence, or mov'd with indignation, made a very eloquent and profitable Oration for the <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> When he had done, <hi>Catiline,</hi> who had the gift of Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with a <hi>demure look, and a low voice,</hi> requeſted the Fathers not to give a raſh credit to every idle Report, but ſhould conſider, that as he was deſcended of a Noble Family, ſo he ever fram'd his life from his Youth up, that he had a proſpect of every thing good and honourable; that they ſhould reflect he was one of their own Order, a <hi>Patrician,</hi> whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had well and nobly deſerv'd for their many Favours and Kindneſſes to the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonalty; that there would be no need of conſpiring the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> ſo long as <hi>M. T. Cicero,</hi> an Inmate, private Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſate at its Helm for its preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Soon as he had ſpoken theſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opprobrious words againſt the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60603:29"/> they were all ſtartl'd, and began to brand him with the diſhonourable terms of Enemy, Monſter, and Parricide: He, with a furious and raging tranſport an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Since I am thus circumvented by my Enemies, the Fire that I have kindled ſhall be quenched by their Ruine.</hi> With that he went haſtily out of the <hi>Senate</hi> to his own houſe, and there ruminated on many things to himſelf, that ſince all his Snares for the <hi>Conſul</hi> prov'd ineffectual, and that the City was ſo well ſecur'd, that there was no poſſibility left of firing it, he thought beſt to increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Army, and before the Legion ſhould be muſter'd, to take ſeveral things with him that might be ſerviceable to him in the War: ſo late at night he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the City, and ſet forward to the Camp of <hi>Manlius;</hi> but gave orders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to <hi>Cethegus</hi> and <hi>Lentulus</hi> (in whoſe boldneſs and reſolution he had the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt confidence) that they ſhould what in them lay, ſtrengthen the Faction, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60603:29"/> to diſpatch the <hi>Conſul,</hi> and get rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Inſtruments of Ruine, and Fire, and other Engines of War, and that he himſelf within a few days would meet them with his Enſigns at the City-walls.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Manlius</hi> ſends a Meſſenger to <hi>Q. Martius Rex,</hi> with ſuch a Meſſage as this:</p>
            <p>We call the Gods and men to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, O General, that we took Arms not to the ruine of our Country, nor to the hazard and detriment of any other; but onely for our own ſecurity, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made miſerable and indigent by the Cruelty and Exaction of our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers,</hi> are out of all hopes of our Country, Fame, and Fortune: for their and the <hi>Praetors</hi> boundleſs Extortion has been ſuch, that we are not allow'd (as our Forefathers were) the uſe and priviledges of our own Laws; and ſince the loſs of our Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, have not had the liberty of our bodies. Many times have our Anceſtors in compaſſion to the <hi>Roman</hi> Commons,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60603:30"/> ſupply'd their neceſſities, and very lately, within our own memories, the greatneſs of their Debts being ſuch, that by the conſent of all good men, Braſs has paſs'd currant inſtead of Silver.</p>
            <p>For the common People being fir'd with the deſire of Command, and juſtly provok'd by the pride and injuſtice of their Magiſtrates, have oftentimes dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the vertues of their Fathers, and ſhook off the heavy Yoak of the <hi>Roman Senate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for us, we neither deſire Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand nor Riches, (the unhappy Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of all the Jars and Diſcontents of mankind) but onely <hi>Liberty, which no good man will ever part with, without life.</hi> We conjure you and the whole <hi>Senate,</hi> to conſult the Quiet and Welfare of the miſerable Citizens, and reſtore them the ſafeguard and defence of thoſe Laws which the Injuſtice and Avarice of the <hi>Praetors</hi> have taken from them: for we would not have it ſaid, that you ſhould
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60603:30"/> impoſe on us the neceſſity of requiring by what means and methods we ſhould fall in the Revenge of our own Bloud.</p>
            <p>To which <hi>Marcius</hi> returned anſwer, That if they intended to have any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Senate,</hi> they ſhould quit their Arms, and return ſubmiſſively to <hi>Rome:</hi> that the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> People were ever of that Generoſity and Clemency, that no Petition of Redreſs of Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was ever in vain, or ineffectual.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Catiline</hi> as he was on his Journey, ſent Letters to many of the Chief of the <hi>Senate,</hi> intimating that he was falſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd of Crimes he knew not; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not withſtand the faction and malice of his Enemies, he thought better to ſubmit to Fortune: that he was gone an <hi>innocent man</hi> to Exile into <hi>Maſſilia,</hi> not becauſe he was guilty of what was laid to his charge, but onely for the quiet of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> whoſe Peace he more ſtudied than any ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Contention, or the vindication of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60603:31"/> his own Innocence. Several Letters of this purport <hi>Catulus</hi> read in the <hi>Senate,</hi> delivered to him in the name of <hi>Catiline;</hi> of which, this was one.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>L. Catiline <hi>to</hi> Q. Catulus, <hi>health.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>YOur extraordinary love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that were ever grateful to me in my greateſt dangers, hath given me the boldneſs for this Commendation; wherefore I thought fit not to ſpeak any thing in my own defence in a new <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> nor to propoſe any ſatisfaction out of any ſelf-guilt of what I am accuſed: which (I take Heaven to witneſs) that you may know the truth, being ſo much provokt by the continual Injuries and Affronts put upon me, being depriv'd of the Fruit and Profit of all my Induſtry, and not obtaining the ſtate of Dignity I ſtood Candidate for, I undertook (as I am wont) the Cauſe of the Afflicted; not but that I could make ſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60603:31"/> for all the Debts contracted on my account out of my own Eſtate, and the Generoſity of <hi>Aurelia Oreſtilla</hi> can ſatisfie the reſt out of her own and her Daughters Revenues: but becauſe I ſaw men worthy of all Honour not preferr'd, and my ſelf alienated from the affections of the <hi>Senate</hi> by a falſe ſuſpition, on this account I proſecuted very honourable hopes of preſerving the reſidue of the Dignity for my own ſake. I would write more, but news is brought me that the <hi>Senate</hi> prepares for Arms: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I commend <hi>Oreſtilla</hi> to your care and protection; defend her from all Injuries, ſince it is the requeſt of us both. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But he himſelf ſtaid a few days with <hi>Flaminius</hi> at <hi>Rheatium,</hi> to ſupply that City with Arms; then with the<note n="*" place="margin">Bundles of Rods carri'd as a mark of Honour and Juſtice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Conſul,</hi> and other great and eminent Officers.</note> 
               <hi>Faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and other Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Enſignes went to the Camp to <hi>Manlius.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60603:32"/>
            <p>Soon as theſe things were known at <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Senate</hi> immediately proclaim'd <hi>Catiline</hi> and <hi>Manlius</hi> Enemies to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick,</hi> and appointed a day for the reſt of the Conſpirators, and thoſe that were already condemn'd for capital Crimes, before they could poſſibly quit their Arms; decreeing likewiſe that the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls</hi> ſhould have a <hi>Dilectum,</hi> and that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> ſhould haſten to follow <hi>Catiline</hi> with his Army, and <hi>Cicero</hi> be leſt for the ſafeguard of the City.</p>
            <p>At that time the Roman Empire ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be in a very low ebb of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; though all their Conqueſts from the Eaſt to the Weſt were at their beck, at home Pleaſures and Riches (the <hi>ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum</hi> of ſome men) flow'd in with a Spring-tyde, yet there were ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Citizens of that perverſe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Spirit, who then endeavour'd what in them lay the Ruine of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth and themſelves too, for the lucre of the Reward promis'd by the two
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60603:32"/> Decretals of the <hi>Senate,</hi> had not that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on one of ſo great a Multitude as to prompt him to diſcover the leaſt particle of the Conſpiracy: neither did one of <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Souldiers prove a <hi>Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado,</hi> ſo much did the <hi>Witchcraft of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion poſſeſs the minds of moſt of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens:</hi> Neither was it the opinion onely of thoſe concern'd in the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> but the greateſt part of the common people were ſo in love with <hi>Reformation,</hi> that they favour'd and approv'd of his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, or at leaſt ſeem'd ſo.</p>
            <p>For always <hi>in a great City all good and loyal perſons become the Envy of the poor and factious:</hi> whereas on the contrary, <hi>wicked Incendiaries are moſt extoll'd;</hi> who hating Antiquities, were in love with Novelties, willing to exchange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Realities for future Uncertainties; being bred and foſter'd onely by Noiſe and Sedition, without any care or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</p>
            <p>For Poverty is eaſily obtain'd without
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60603:33"/> loſs, but the common Citizens urged themſelves headlong to their own ruine, eſpecially thoſe who excelled others in Cheats and Cozenage; ſecondly, thoſe whoſe loſs of Patrimony was attended with diſgrace and neceſſity; and laſtly, thoſe whom any wicked and nefarious Villany had baniſht <hi>Rome:</hi> Theſe at that time fled to the City as to a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel; and many calling to remembrance the Uſurpation of <hi>Sylla,</hi> that they ſaw ſome from common Souldiers become Senators; others ſo opulent, that they liv'd rather like Princes than common Subjects; every one hop'd that if Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory attended their Swords, the ſame or a better fortune: Beſides, the Country Youth, who earn'd their Bread in the fields by the ſweat of their brows, being fir'd with their profuſe prodigality both in private and <hi>publick,</hi> preferr'd the idle life and pleaſures of the City before the ungrateful toyl and labour of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60603:33"/>
            <p>Not onely theſe, but all, were infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the ſame diſeaſe; by which it is the leſs to be admir'd that indigent perſons, indued with ill principles, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch hopes, conſulted not ſo much the good of the <hi>Republick,</hi> as their own intereſts: beſides, thoſe whoſe Parents were baniſht, and had their Eſtates <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred,</hi> and their Rights and Priviledges leſſen'd by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> of <hi>Sylla,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the Event of this War to be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle different from that. Moreover, thoſe who were of a different Opinion and Party from that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, had rather the Commonwealth ſhould be diſturb'd, than they themſelves be the leſs quiet. Thus the old Miſchief, after the revolution of ſome years, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to infect the City once agen.</p>
            <p>For when the Power of the<note n="*" place="margin">Of which there were two ſorts, <hi>Tribunis militum,</hi> who had onely authority in matters military; and <hi>Tribuni Plebis,</hi> Protectors of the People, <hi>Anglicè,</hi> Sheriffs.</note> 
               <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes</hi> was reſtor'd (in the Conſulate of <hi>Cn. Pompeius,</hi> and <hi>M. Craſſus</hi>) the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60603:34"/> Roman Youth, having attain'd the height of Power, their Age and Spirits being alike ſierce and untam'd, began to irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the <hi>Rabble</hi> by criminating the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Senate;</hi> and by degrees in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing them more and more by Bribes and Promiſes, made themſelves very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularly famous. On the contrary, moſt of the Nobility of the <hi>Senate,</hi> for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and their own <hi>Grandeur,</hi> endeavour'd what in them lay to oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>But after that <hi>Cn. Pompeius</hi> was ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the <hi>Maritime</hi> and <hi>Mithridatick</hi> War<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Riches of the common People were diminiſht, and the Empire fell into the hands of a few. Theſe men had al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Magiſtracies, Provinces,</hi> and every thing elſe in their own poſſeſſion, and were altogether abſolute and uncontroulable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leading their lives without any fear o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> danger, and aw'd all others by the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of their Laws to reduce the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty into a better Obedience: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60603:34"/> the firſt opportunity that offer'd any hopes, blew up the Coals of Diſſention afreſh within them. But to return.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Catiline</hi> had departed <hi>Rome</hi> at firſt, with an Army equal to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a mighty Slaughter and Calamity had inevitably befallen it; neither would thoſe who had been victorious have been long able to retain their Conqueſt, but he that had the ſtronger Party would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Empire from the more weak and infirm.</p>
            <p>Beſides thoſe that were now concern'd in the Conſpiracy, there were ſome who ſided with <hi>Catiline</hi> before; among theſe was one <hi>Fulvius</hi> the Son of a Senator, whom being taken in his Journey, his Father commanded to be ſlain. At that time at <hi>Rome</hi> was alſo <hi>Lentulus,</hi> who by the inſtigation of <hi>Catiline</hi> ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (either by himſelf or others) all, whoſe Manners and Fortunes he thought render'd them deſirous of <hi>Reformation;</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60603:35"/> not onely Citizens, but all ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that might aid a War.</p>
            <p>To that purpoſe he employs one <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brenus</hi> to ſollicite to Embaſſadours of the<note n="*" place="margin">A very fierce and Warlike People that inhabited ſome part of <hi>Gallila,</hi> and were tributaries to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Now Inhabitants of <hi>Dauphiny</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Allobroges,</hi> and decoy them, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, into the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing (as indeed they were) that they were deeply taxed both abroad and at home. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over he knew the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtinus ex Trogo.</hi> Non reges Orientis ſine Mercenario Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum Exercítu, ulla bella Geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt, tantus terror Gallici No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, ſive armorum, invicta felicitas erat, ut alter neque Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem ſuam tutam, neque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſam recuperare ſe poſſe, ſine Gallica virtute arbitrarentur.</note> 
               <hi>Gauls</hi> were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally a fierce and <hi>warlike</hi> People, and might eaſily be brought over to ſuch a Deſigne. This <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrenus</hi> was known to, and well acquainted with the Chiefs and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of all their Cities, becauſe he had for ſome time been employed in <hi>Gallia</hi> by the <hi>Roman Senate;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60603:35"/> he took an opportunity when he ſaw the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours in the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Forum</hi> has ſeveral ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but I ſuppoſe this to be the place where Orations were made to the People, and where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Law were judicial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determin'd.</note> 
               <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> asking them a few Queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſtate and condition of their City, and as it were condoling their Misfortunes, he began to inquire of them what end they hop'd to expect of all their Miſeries; but when he heard them complain of the covetouſneſs of their Magiſtrates, that they accus'd the <hi>Roman Senate</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they afforded them no Redreſs, and that they expected nothing but Death to be their Remedy; But I (ſaid he) provided you will ſhew your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s;elves men, can put you into a method how you may eaſily avoid theſe Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
            <p>When he had ſaid this, the <hi>Allobro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> big with expectation, entreated
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60603:36"/> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrenus</hi> to commiſerate their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promis'd that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo hard and difficult, but they would to the utmoſt of their power en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to accompliſh, if by any means poſſible he could deliver their Citie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the rigour of their Taxes.</p>
            <p>Preſently he leads them into the houſe of <hi>Decius Brutus,</hi> becauſe 'twa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> near the <hi>Forum,</hi> and was their general Rendezvouz, for the ſake of his Wif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sempronia;</hi> (for <hi>Brutus</hi> was at tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time abſent from <hi>Rome:</hi>) to his aid h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> calls <hi>Gabinius,</hi> who was endued with the better Art of Perſwaſion; in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he opens the whole Plot, and to induce them the more, diſcovers th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Confederates and the reſt that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd therein: and when they had conſented, and promis'd what Aid they could afford, they were diſmiſs'd.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60603:36"/>
            <p>But the <hi>Allobroges</hi> were long in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe what Courſe to ſteer; on the one ſide, were their Debts and Exactions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of War, and a proſpect of the vaſt Rewards of Victory; on the other, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Riches and Aids, ſafe Counſel, and inſtead of uncertain Hopes, certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Conſulting theſe things, at length Fortune favour'd the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this they diſcover'd what they knew to <hi>Q. Fabius Sanga,</hi> (under whoſe Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their City then was) <hi>Cicero</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it by <hi>Sanga,</hi> order'd the Embaſſadors ſtill ſeemingly to favour the Conſpiracy, accordingly to meet them, promiſe them vvell, and do their Endeavour to make themſelves acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with as much as poſſible. About the ſame time were there Inſurrections in both <hi>Gallia</hi>'s, in the Territories of <hi>Pice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and at <hi>Brutium</hi> in <hi>Apulia;</hi> for thoſe whom <hi>Catiline</hi> had ſent away before, raſhly and inconſiderately manag'd eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, according to their own Will, and caus'd more Fear than Danger by
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60603:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60603:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60603:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60603:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60603:39"/> their nightly <hi>Cabal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Conveyance of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and Darts, by their urging and haſtening every thing; of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Quintus Metellus Celer</hi> (being made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it by the Senate) put ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny into Chains and Irons; the like did <hi>C. Muraena</hi> in yonder <hi>Gallia,</hi> who was Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of that <hi>Province.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at <hi>Rome, Lentulus,</hi> with the reſt of the Chief of the Conſpiracy that were ready with their Forces, ſo deſign'd it, that as ſoon as <hi>Catiline</hi> was come into <hi>Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulae</hi> with his Army, <hi>L. Beſtia,</hi> the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People, ſhould in a ſelect Oration lay the blame of the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding upon <hi>Cicero,</hi> and lay the Envy of the moſt unheard of Wars upon the beſt of <hi>Conſuls,</hi> and by a certain ſignal the reſt of the Conſpirators the next Night ſhould ſeverally proſecute their intended miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, but in this method, that <hi>Statilius</hi> and <hi>Gabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius,</hi> with a ſmall Party, ſhould ſet fire on twelve chief Places of the City; by which means they might the better come at the <hi>Conſul</hi> and the reſt for whom
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60603:39"/> they had laid wait; that <hi>Cathegus</hi> ſhould beſet the Gate of <hi>Cicero,</hi> and aſſaſſinate him, ſome one way and ſome another; but the Sons of Families (of which the moſt part was of the Nobility) ſhould kill their own Parents. So that every one being thunder-ſtruck as it were with Blood and Fire, ſhould confuſedly run out, and joyn with <hi>Catiline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were deſigning and preparing, <hi>Cethegus</hi> continually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of the Sloth and Lazineſs of his Companions, that their doubting and delays had loſt them ſeveral fair and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing Opportunities, and that there was more need of Action than Council, in a matter of ſo great and dangerous a Conſequence, that he himſelf with the help of a few more (ſince the reſt were ſo remiſs) would ſet upon, and maſſacre the whole Senate. This <hi>Cethegus</hi> was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally fierce and cruel, very dexterous, and ſucceſsful in what he undertook, and ever thought the greateſt Honour of any Action conſiſted in <hi>Celerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60603:40"/>
            <p>But the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> according to the Command of <hi>Cicero,</hi> met <hi>Gabinius</hi> and the reſt, and required an Oath of <hi>Lentulus, Cethegus, Statilius,</hi> and <hi>Caſsius,</hi> which being ſeal'd, would be a ſure Pledge or Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to their Citizens, without which it would be very difficult to induce them to favour ſo great and hazardous a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, which they (not at all ſuſpecting) freely gave. <hi>Caſsius</hi> promiſed to come thither in a ſhort time, to command what Aid they ſhould afford, and accordingly departed the City a little before the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours. He alſo ſent with them <hi>P. Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turtius,</hi> to the end the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> before they return'd home, ſhould confirm the <hi>Aſſociation</hi> with <hi>Catiline,</hi> by a mutual Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, himſelf likewiſe deliver'd Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Vulturtius</hi> for <hi>Catiline,</hi> of which this is one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who I am the Bearer ſhall acquaint you, Conſider in how great a Calamity you at preſent are, remember that you are a man, and a</hi> Roman, <hi>and what the preſent poſture of your Affairs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60603:40"/> get what Aid you can from every one, even the moſt vile and abject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He order'd likewiſe <hi>Vulturtius</hi> to inform <hi>Catiline,</hi> that ſince the <hi>Senate</hi> had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him Enemy to the Commonwealth, by what means he ſhould refuſe their Conditions if offer'd, that all things were ready in the City, which he gave Orders for, and that he ſhould no longer delay to advance nearer.</p>
            <p>Theſe things done, <hi>Cicero</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of all by the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Praetors, L. Valerius Flaccus,</hi> and <hi>C. Pomptinius,</hi> by ambuſh to ſeiſe the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> and their retinue on the <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> bridge. The ſame night that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, accordingly they appointed ſome armed Men without any noiſe or tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult to beſet the Bridge; where, when the Ambaſſadours with <hi>Vulturtius</hi> came, the word given, on both ſides the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh broke forth, the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> knowing the Deſign, willingly ſurrendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but <hi>Vulturtius</hi> at firſt encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the reſt, defended himſelf from the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60603:41"/> multitude with his Sword, but when he ſaw himſelf deſerted by the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, he intreated many things of <hi>Pomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinius,</hi> for his own ſafety; and fearful, and diſtruſtimg his life, deliver'd himſelf Priſoner to the <hi>Praetors,</hi> of which thing <hi>Cicero</hi> had very ſeaſonable notice, and 'twas hard to diſcern whether his Joy or Care was the greater, he was glad when he conſider'd, that by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of ſo great a Treaſon the City was ſecure from all its threatening Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and was Anxious and Doubtful what to do, ſince ſuch great Citizens were apprehended in ſo dangerous a Deſign, whoſe Envy he muſt needs incur, and conſider'd that their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be the trouble, and their Impunity the ruine of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> therefore with a reſolute Courage he commanded <hi>Lentulus, Cethegus, Statilius,</hi> and <hi>Gabinius</hi> to be call'd before him, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Ceparius,</hi> who was preparing to go for <hi>Apulia,</hi> to raiſe Forces; the reſt immediately came, but <hi>Ceparius</hi> a little
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60603:41"/> before going from home, happen'd to underſtand the Deſign, and fled the City. The <hi>Conſul</hi> taking <hi>Lentulus</hi> by the hand becauſe he was <hi>Praetor,</hi> led him into the Senate, but the reſt he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to attend him in the Houſe of <hi>Concord,</hi> thither he aſſembl'd the Senate, and ſeveral of that Order introduc'd <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turtius</hi> and the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> and <hi>Flaccus</hi> the <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> with the Packet of Letters he found with the Ambaſſadours. <hi>Vulturtius</hi> being demanded ſeveral things concerning the Journey and Letters, what was their Deſign and Purpoſe, and on what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he did ſo, at firſt fain'd, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembl'd every thing, pretending he knew nothing, and <hi>was only travelling</hi> for <hi>Gallia,</hi> but when he had the Senates faith, and the <hi>Conſul</hi>'s word to fortify him, he made a full diſcovery of every Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that he was drawn in by <hi>Gabinius</hi> and <hi>Ceparius</hi> into the Conſpiracy, that he knew no more than what he heard the Embaſſadours ſay, that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by <hi>Gabinius,</hi> that <hi>P. Autronius, Ser.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60603:42"/> Sylla, L. Vargunteius,</hi> and ſeveral others were Confederates in the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> the ſame was Declar'd by the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, but they prov'd <hi>Lentulus</hi> guilty, not only by the Letters, but by ſome <hi>Speeches</hi> which he uſually made uſe of. Concerning the Books of the<note n="*" place="margin">Of which there were ten, who all prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Saviour:</hi> The place wherein their Books were kept, was within the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol, under ground, in a Cheſt of Stone, where they remain'd ſafe till the firing of the Capitol, wherein they were burn't too.</note> 
               <hi>Sybills,</hi> that three <hi>Cornelii</hi> were to reign in <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Cinna</hi> and <hi>Sylla</hi> were paſt before, and that he was the third, whoſe Fate it was to obtain the Sovereignty of the City that year, the Twentieth from the Firing of the<note n="*" place="margin">So call'd from a man's head ſound in the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foundation, on the <hi>Tarpeian</hi> mount, begun to be built, <hi>An.</hi> urbis 127, perfected <hi>Anno</hi> urb: 247, burnt <hi>Anno</hi> urb: 670.</note> 
               <hi>Capitol,</hi> which by Prodigies, the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic dict: ab aras Inſpiciendo,</hi> that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin'd, or foretold things by the Entrails of Beaſts ſacrific'd.</note> 
               <hi>Aruſpices</hi> predicted to be very fatal to the City by a Civil War.</p>
            <p>When they had read all the Letters, and every of the Conſpirators had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged their Seals, the Senate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60603:42"/> That <hi>Lentulus</hi> ſhould put off his <hi>Praetorſhip,</hi> and with the reſt be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to free Priſons. <hi>Lentulus</hi> was committed to <hi>P. Lentulus Spinther,</hi> who was then <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile, Cethegus</hi> to <hi>Q. Cornificius, Statilius</hi> to <hi>C. Caeſar, Gabinius</hi> to M. <hi>Craſſus, Ceparius</hi> (who was taken in his flight) to <hi>Cn. Terentius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Plot thus far diſcover'd, the Common People, who before were ſo deſirous of Novelties, and too much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd the War, chang'd their Opinions, and began to execrate the Deſigns of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiline,</hi> extoll'd <hi>Cicero</hi> to the Stars, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated all manner of Joy and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, as if they had been freed from an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Slavery; for they knew that War, undertaken upon any other terms, was more for plunder than deſtruction: but this being deſign'd for fire and ruin, they knew to be immoderately cruel and calamitous to themſelves.</p>
            <p>The next day after, one <hi>L. Tarquinius</hi> was brought to the <hi>Senate,</hi> who was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as he was going to <hi>Catiline;</hi> he, when
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60603:43"/> he promis'd to diſcover as much as he knew of the Conſpiracy, had the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Faith for the ſecurity of his Life. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded to it by the Conſul, he related almoſt the ſame with <hi>Vulturtius,</hi> of the preparations for firing the City, the maſſacring of the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> and the March of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Moreover, he ſaid he was ſent by <hi>M. Craſſus,</hi> to tell <hi>Catiline</hi> that he ſhould not be diſcouraged at the calamitous mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of <hi>Lentulus</hi> and <hi>Cethegus</hi> that were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, but ſhould the rather haſten to approach the City, that he might put freſh Courage into the Breaſts of the reſt, and more eaſily deliver them from the threatning Danger. But when <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> nam'd <hi>Craſſus,</hi> a Nobleman of vaſt Riches, and no leſs Power, ſome thought it to be incredible, others, tho they thought it true, yet thought better that the power of ſo great a Perſon ſhould be rather pacifi'd than exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But many that depended on <hi>Craſſus,</hi> for their own intereſt, gave out, that the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60603:43"/> Evidence was falſe, and deſir'd that the matter might be laid aſide; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the advice of <hi>Cicero,</hi> the whole Senate decreed, that the Evidence of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius</hi> was altogether falſe, and that he ſhould be kept cloſe Priſoner in Irons; Neither ſhould confeſs any more till he diſcover'd by vvhoſe Advice he ſhould frame ſo great a Lye on ſo Worthy and Noble a Citizen.</p>
            <p>At that time, there were not wanting ſome that imagined this trick to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd by <hi>P. Antronius,</hi> that <hi>Craſſus</hi> being made a Confederate in the Danger, the greatneſs of his Power might protect the reſt. Others reported, that this <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> was ſent in by <hi>Cicero,</hi> leſt <hi>Craſſus</hi> ſhould take the Conſpirators into his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, and ſo diſturb the Quiet of the <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> Not long ſince, I heard this <hi>Craſſus</hi> himſelf declaim, wherein he affirms <hi>Cicero</hi> to be the Author of ſo great a Contumely; yet at the ſame time <hi>Q. Catulus</hi> and <hi>Cn Piſo,</hi> could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Favour, Intreaties, nor Bribes,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60603:44"/> prevail with <hi>Cicero,</hi> that <hi>C. Caeſar</hi> ſhould be falſly accus'd, either by the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> or any other Evidence, for both theſe were great Enemies to <hi>Caeſar, Piſo</hi> being by him accus'd of Bribery in the open <hi>Senate,</hi> for the unjuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a certain<note n="*" place="margin">So call'd from the other ſide of the River <hi>Po</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> where they inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</note> 
               <hi>Tranſpadani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> and <hi>Catulus</hi> hated him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in his latter years, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving undergone all Offices and Honours, vvhen he ſtood Candidate for the <hi>Pontificate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pontificate was an Office to have the over ſight of a Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bridge, call'd <hi>Pons Sublicius,</hi> being ſo great that Carts might paſs over it, having no Arches to uphold it, but only great Poſts and Piles of Wood, and that which is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in it is, that it is joyn'd together only with wooden Pins, without any Iron at all.</note> yet young <hi>Caeſar</hi> vvas preferred before him. But when by no means imaginable they could make the Conſul guilty of ſo great a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, they themſelves by counterfeiting his Seal, and inſinuating what they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to underſtand from <hi>Vulturtius,</hi> and the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> contracted on him a great deal of Envy; inſomuch that ſome <hi>Roman</hi> Knights, who were there plac'd, arm'd with Darts for a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60603:44"/> Defence to the Houſe of <hi>Concord,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of apprehenſion of the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Danger, or greatneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that their Zeal to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth might be the more apparent, threatned <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as he went out of the <hi>Senate,</hi> with their Swords.</p>
            <p>While theſe things were doing in the <hi>Senate,</hi> and Rewards decreed to <hi>Vultur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and the <hi>Allobroges</hi> for their approv'd Evidence, the Servants and Clients of <hi>Lentulus</hi> were continually ſolliciting the Tradeſ-men, and Hirelings in the Streets, to deliver him by force; others made Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt with the Ring-leaders of the Rabble, who uſually for Pay and Reward, made factious Inſurrections in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: <hi>Cethegus</hi> on the other ſide ſent Meſſengers to ſollicit his own Family, and the Chief of his <hi>Liberti,</hi> that were train'd up in bold and daring Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, that getting an head, they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue him by force of Arms.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as this came to the Conſul's Ears, he ſet ſuch Guards and Watches
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60603:45"/> over them as he thought convenient and neceſſary, and aſſembling the Senate, demanded what they intended to do with the Conſpirators they had in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, who in a full Senate were found guilty of Treaſon againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>D. Junius Silanus,</hi> becauſe he was next deſign'd Conſul, being ask't his Judgment, not only againſt thoſe that were already in Cuſtody, but alſo againſt <hi>L. Caſsius, P. Furius, P. Umbrenus,</hi> and <hi>Q. Annius,</hi> if they ſhould be taken, he Decreed they ſhould ſuffer ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the Laws require.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ask'd his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſpoke after this manner.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Conſcript Fathers,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Sic Demoſth. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c.</note>THoſe who conſult of things dubious and dangerous ought to be free from all Hatred, Love, Wrath, or Pity; for that Man can never throughly look into the end of any thing when he is by aſs'd by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60603:45"/> any one of theſe; neither can he at the ſame time indulge his own Humour and be ſerviceable to the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> where once Fancy takes place 'tis always preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, if Luſt, it always commands; ſo that <hi>Reaſon</hi> becomes loſt and ineffectual: I could give you large Examples, <hi>Fathers,</hi> of ſeveral Kings and Nations, who, led either by Prejudice or Pity, have given wrong Judgments; but I had rather treat of ſome of the Actions of our ovvn Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, vvho againſt the Current of their ovvn Humours and Inclinations, have rightly and impartially adminiſtred Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Macedonian</hi> War, which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire wag'd with King <hi>Perſeus</hi> the Great, and ſtately City of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> which grew famous by the Riches of the <hi>Roman</hi> People, was very treacherouſly revolted from us. Our Anceſtors, when they were to give Sentence on the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> leſt any ſhould report he made War for the ſake of Wealth or Injuries, ſent them home unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd. So likewiſe in all the <hi>Carthaginian</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60603:46"/> Wars, though in Peace, and Ceſſation of Arms, they committed many nefarious Villanies, yet they conſulted more their own Honour than the Rigour of the Law. So theſe, O <hi>Conſcript</hi> Fathers, ſhould be your Examples. Let not the Treaſon of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and the reſt, make your Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtrike ſail to your Revenge; neither let any immoderate Paſſion prevail more with you than the Senſe of your own Fame and Grandeur: for, if you could find out any Puniſhment equal to their Crimes, I ſhould willingly conſent to it; but if the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Wickedneſs is beyond all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Apprehenſion, I think ſuch Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are to be inflicted as the Laws pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe who have given their Judgments before, have very accurately and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly commiſerated the ſad Condition of the Commonwealth, and ſumm'd up what the inhumane Cruelty of the War would be, and what diſmal Extremities had been the Fate of the Conquer'd, our Virgins would have been raviſh'd, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60603:46"/> pull'd from the dear Embraces of their frighted Parents, and Matrons ſuffer all the baſe Abuſes that the unbridl'd Luſt of Conquerours can invent, Temples and Houſes ſack'd and plunder'd, Slaughter, and Fire raging in our Streets, and every thing look with the horrid Aſpect of Blood and Ruine. This was the only Mark they aim'd at; but to what Purpoſe is all this Oration? Is it to incenſe you more againſt their Treaſon? Or can a fine Oration make it more hated than its own Nature? Every Man thinks his own Injuries not light and trivial, and moſt endeavour to revenge them with greater Paſſion than they ought; inferiour States and petty Republicks may change and alter upon Humour, when if they offend and puniſh partially, 'tis known but to a few, becauſe they are obſcure; for both their Fame and Fortunes hang in an <hi>Aequilibrio,</hi> and run in one and the ſame Channel; but they that are the Maſters of the Univerſe, and live in that ſeen and conſpicuous height of Fortune, all Mankind become Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60603:47"/> of their Actions: ſo that the more great and honourable they are, the leſs is their Liberty: for they muſt not in the leaſt hate or favour any one, nor in the leaſt be angry, for what in others is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Anger, in Men endu'd with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Empire is call'd Pride and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty. I think, Fathers, that the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Torments are inferiour to their Crimes; but moſt Men have reſpect to things paſt, and on impious Perſons, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting their Wickedneſs; they differ, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning the Puniſhment, if any thing more ſevere than ordinary. I know <hi>Sylanus,</hi> who ſpoke before me, to be a Loyal and Couragious Gentleman, and what he ſpoke to be only for the Good and Honour of the Commonwealth, that he would not in ſo great a Buſineſs make uſe either of Favour or Hatred; neither are his Manners nor his Moderation unknown to me, nor do I think his Sentence cruel or ſevere, (for what can be too much ſo againſt ſuch Delinquents) but that it is unuſual and hating to the <hi>Republick;</hi> but
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60603:47"/> indeed, <hi>Sylanus</hi> (our deſign'd <hi>Conſul</hi>) fear muſt certainly poſſ ſs thee, thus to decree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> new and unheard of kind of Puniſhment; but 'tis ſuperfluous to talk of Fear, when every thing is made ſo ſafe and ſecure by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Diligence and Conduct of ſo worthy a <hi>Conſul</hi> and ſuch ſtrong, Guards.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Puniſhment, I can only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay what the nature of the Thing requires; for<note n="*" place="margin">Sic <hi>Cicero,</hi> ita vivere, ut non ſit vivendam, miſerrimum est: mori autem nemo ſapiens miſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum duxit, ne beato quidem. Et <hi>Eurip.</hi> in <hi>Theſeo,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Death is the end of all Grief and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies, and is rather a pleaſing Reſt than a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ormenting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt; it diſſolves all humane Troubles and Afflictions, and is the only Period to all Pains and Pleaſures; but (by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al Gods) Why did you not condemn them to be ſcourg'd? Is it becauſe forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the <hi>Portian</hi> Law? But other Laws alſo command Baniſhment, and not Death, to condemn'd Citizens; or is't becauſe Death ſeems a greater Puniſhment than Stripes? For indeed there can be nothing too cruel and ſevere on Men convicted of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60603:48"/> ſuch palpable and notorious Villanies? Or becauſe it is more tolerable for Men to fear the Law in a leſs Matter when you neglect to inflict it in a greater? But who is there can find fault in any Puniſhment decreed on <hi>Parricides?</hi> For whatever is inflicted on ſuch is juſt and deſerved; but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Fathers,</hi> that all ill Examples had their firſt Springs and Original from good but when baſe and undeſerving Perſons are inveſted with Command and Empire, the Example too is alter'd, and the Empire tranſlated.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lacaedemonians,</hi> when they had conquer'd <hi>Athens,</hi> impos'd on them <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Men (or rather Tyrants)</hi> to manage the Affairs of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> theſe at firſt began to put to Death every baſe and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Citizen, which the Common-people commended as juſt and meritorious; but ſoon after, when with their Power their Luſt encreaſed, they made no Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to put to Death Innocents and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors alike, and us'd Threats and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, as the only means to keep the reſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60603:48"/> in awe. Thus the City became oppreſt with Slavery, and ſuffer'd a juſt Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their fooliſh Commendation. Within our own Memories, the <hi>Uſurper Sylla,</hi> when he commanded<note n="*" place="margin">A Baſe <hi>Roman,</hi> that took part with <hi>Marius</hi> againſt <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> and ſacrificed Men among <hi>Beaſts.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Damaſippus</hi> and the reſt of his Accomplices, (who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd the Subverſion of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) to be ſtrangl'd, who was there did not applaud his Juſtice? Every one prais'd it, that wicked facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Citizens, that ſow'd Seditions in the <hi>Republick</hi> had deſerved Puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted on them; but that was but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to a far greater Ruine; for as then any one that coveted another's Houſe, Farm, Veſſel, or Garment, and could not obtain it, endeavour'd to put the other into the Number of the Proſcript, ſo thoſe that then rejoyc'd at the Death of <hi>Damaſippus</hi> were themſelves made Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his Fate; neither did their Blood and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ruine ceaſe till <hi>Sylla</hi> rais'd the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of his own Party to a conſiderable height; but we at preſent have no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60603:49"/> to fear the like under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo good a <hi>Conſul</hi> as <hi>M. Tullius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> but in ſo great a City as ours are a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of factious and various Humours At another time, and under another <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul,</hi> who has the Command of the Army in his own Hands, what may now ſeem impoſſible may then paſs for true and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and when once the <hi>Conſul</hi> ſhall give the firſt Example of drawing the Sword, who is there will oppoſe or controul him? Our Anceſtors Fathers never yet needed either Courage or Counſel, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were ſo ſway'd by Pride and Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, as not to imitate the manners of others, if good and vertuous: They had firſt their Arms and Military Darts from the <hi>Sammites,</hi> the Trophies of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy from the <hi>Tuſcans,</hi> and wherever they ſaw any thing uſeful and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, either in Friends of Enemies, that, with the greateſt Care and induſtry, they embrac'd and follow'd: they had rather imitate than envy any thing good and commendable; but at that ſame time
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60603:49"/> imitating the Manners of <hi>Greece,</hi> they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Stripes on Citizens, and Death on other condemn'd Malefactors; but when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Commonwealth grew up, and the multitude of Citizens produced likewiſe a multitude of Factions, both the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and Guilty partak'd of one and the ſame Puniſhment; then the <hi>Portian,</hi> and other Laws were provided, which Laws <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpos'd only Baniſhment on condemn'd Citizens; therefore I think the Reaſons I have given why they ſhould not dye, are very weighty; for indeed the Vertue and Wiſdom of our Fore-fathers was the more eminent and conſpicuous, who from ſuch ſmall Aid and Treaſures rais'd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to ſo great an height, than in us, who can ſcarce preſerve what they with ſo much Labour and Induſtry have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd. But do you think I would have them ſent out, and make an Addition to <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Army? No, but my Sentence is, that their Eſtates ſhould be confiſcated, and they themſelves remain Priſoners in Irons in the Municipal Towns vvhich
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60603:50"/> are moſt fortify'd, neither hereafter ſhall they have any relation to the Senate, or any thing to do vvith the <hi>Roman People,</hi> vvhich if they have, the <hi>Senate</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree it done againſt the Republick, and the common Safety of us all.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as <hi>Caeſar</hi> had ended, ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded, others diſlik'd it; ſome were of one Opinion, ſome of another, but <hi>M. P. Cato,</hi> being ask'd his Sentence, ſpoke to this purpoſe;</p>
                  <p>My Judgment, Fathers, is much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that of <hi>Caius Caeſar,</hi> when I compare the Aſſociation it ſelf and our own Danger with the Sentence already given; they diſpute what kind of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to inflict on thoſe that have conſpir'd to make War againſt their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Fathers,</hi> and their own <hi>Religion,</hi> for we ſhould rather ſtudy to beware ſuch, than what to inflict on them; other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences the Laws may proſecute when committed, but this, if ye prevent not e're it happen, if once happen'd, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60603:50"/> you decree againſt it, will be vain, and to no purpoſe; for if once they make themſelves Maſters of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we that are the conquer'd ſhall have nothing left us to enjoy, wherefore I conjure you, that if ever you thought your <hi>Houſes, Farms, Statues,</hi> and your <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Tables</hi> to he continued, by the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Peace and Quiet, if you intend ſtill to continue what you now enjoy, and to have time and leiſure to indulge your Pleaſures; now at length awake, and conſult the Preſervation of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> for we do not now contend for Stipends, and Tributes, nor complain of the Injuries of our Confederates, but our Liberty and very Lives lye almoſt on the very brink of Ruin. Oftentimes, <hi>Fathers,</hi> in this <hi>Senate,</hi> have I declaim'd againſt the <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> of our own <hi>Citizens, and have raiſed many Enemies to me for that very reaſon:</hi> for I, who never in any meaſure favour'd the Offences of any one, would not now be eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to pardon the many Trayterous
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60603:51"/> Extravagances of others Luſts; but theſe things, tho you accounted trivial, made the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> remain ſecure and undiſturb'd, for their extraordinary Riches gave their Negligence a greater toleration. But the Diſpute is not now whether we ſhould regulate our Lives by good or ill Examples, nor how to render the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> more great and Splendid, but all theſe things, we at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoy, and ſeem to have in a quiet poſſeſſion, will by our own Sloth and neglect, become a Prey to our Enemies. In vain therefore doth<note n="*" place="margin">C. Caeſar.</note> He uſe the Names of Clemency and Pity, ſince long ſince we have loſt the uſe of both, becauſe profuſe ſpending another man's Eſtate has obtain'd the ſpecious term of Liberality, and a wicked Impudence that of true Valour; and by this means comes it that the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is in ſo dangerous a poſture. But allow men to be laviſh of other men's Fortunes, ſince 'tis the <hi>mode,</hi> and let pity be ſhown to thoſe that rob the <hi>publick</hi> Treaſury; but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60603:51"/> let them not be prodigal of our Blood, and under pretence of being pittiful to a few loſt and diſſolute men, promote the ruin of all the Good.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>C. Caeſar</hi> here hath very well and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly diſcours'd of Life and Death, as if he thought thoſe things only fictitious which are deliver'd to us, of <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and the <hi>ſhades below,</hi> and of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent wayes that wicked men go from good, to gloomy, dark, and ugly abodes, and therefore decrees that their Eſtates ſhould be confiſcate, and they kept Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners in the free Towns, fearing, leſt if they ſhould ſtill remain in <hi>Rome,</hi> either by the Confederates of the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or the giddy Rabble, they ſhould have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue, as if <hi>Rome</hi> was the only Neſt and Receptacle of wicked <hi>Debauchees,</hi> and not all <hi>Italy;</hi> or that a daring Impudence would not commit moſt outrage, where it met with the leaſt reſiſtance. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think his Counſel to be vain and frivolous, and if in ſo great a Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation he alone ſtands unfrighted, we
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60603:52"/> have all reaſon to fear him. Thoſe things which you decree concerning <hi>Lentulus,</hi> I would have you to reſolve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole Army of <hi>Catiline,</hi> for by how much the more ſeverely you do this, the fainter and the more infirm will their Courage be, but if they ſee you in the leaſt remiſs and languid, the fiercer Aſſault muſt ye expect from them; flatter not your ſelves therefore with the Opinion, that your Anceſtors rais'd the <hi>Republick</hi> to what it now is, from ſmall and indigent, to ſo great and famous; for if it were ſo, we have much the more reaſon to continue it in its preſent Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, becauſe we have greater Forces, of Allies and Citizens, Armour and Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, than ever they had. But there were other things that rendred them renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which we have not; <hi>at home Induſtry, abroad, a lawfully acquir'd Empire, a mind free in Councel, not in the leaſt ſway'd by Pride or Debauchery: Inſtead of theſe, we abound in Luxury and Avarice, in Diſcredit and Debts abroad, at home in Eaſe and Plenty; we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60603:52"/> Riches, but embrace Idleneſs, and make no difference between Good and Ill, ſince Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ingroſſes all the Rewards of Virtue; neither is it ſtrange, ſince ye all conſult the Good of the Republick, only apart and ſeparate, while in the mean time you are Slaves to your Pleaſures at home, and here to Intereſt, and the Favour of others.</hi> Thence it is that Attempts are made upon the Naked and unarm'd <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth:</hi> but I paſs this by.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>the Noblest Citizens have conſpir'd to imbroyl their Country in a Civil-War,</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to their Aid the <hi>Gauls,</hi> a People war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and fierce, ever envious of, and full of Hatred to the <hi>Roman</hi> Greatneſs: the Commander of our Enemies is juſt upon us, and you yet ſtill delay to ſuppreſs them, and are yet dubious what Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to inflict on Traytors apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within our own Walls. I ſuppoſe you are pitiful, ſince ſuch <hi>Young Noblemen have offended only through Ambition,</hi> and you would fain diſmiſs them arm'd; yet your Clemency and Pity would, if they ſhould take Arms, turn to your own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60603:53"/> The matter it ſelf is really dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, but you neither fear nor apprehend it: here, through Sloth and a Womaniſh Softneſs, you look one on another, as if you truſted to the Immortal Gods, who have often preſerved the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> in its greateſt Dangers. <hi>No faint Wiſhes nor effeminate Prayers can draw them to your Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, but by</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cicero ſic de finibus,</hi> minime convenit, cum ipſi inter nos ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecti, neglecti ſue famus peſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare, Si diis immortalibus Chari ſumus, &amp; ab his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamur. <hi>Et Gellius,</hi> Quid nos à diis immortalibus diuti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s expectemus, niſi malis ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſinem facimus?</note> 
               <hi>Vigilance, Counſel, and Action, you may juſtly expect a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Delivery: but, when once you give your ſelves up to Sloth and Idleneſs, (which they hate) all Prayers and Devotions to the Gods are lost and ineffectual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt our Anceſtors, <hi>Aulus Manlius Torquatus</hi> commanded his own Son to be ſlain, becauſe, contrary to Command, he fought for the Republick againſt their Enemies. But that extraordinary young Man ſuffered Death as a juſt Puniſhment for ſuch an immoderate and unſeaſonable Valour, and yet you differ concerning the Puniſhment of the moſt unheard of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60603:53"/> 
               <hi>Parricides:</hi> yet I would have you in ſome meaſure to commiſerate the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Dignity of <hi>Lentulus.</hi> If he had had any pity for it himſelf, or any regard to the Honour of the Gods and the Lives of us all, pardon the Extravagance of Young <hi>Cethegus;</hi> if ye are ſo far in love with Civil War, as to let him make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Attempt; and what ſhall I tell you of <hi>Gabinius, Statilius,</hi> and <hi>Ceparius?</hi> who, had they any love for the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and their own Countrey, had never ſo dangerouſly conſpir'd againſt them. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, Fathers, (ſhould I not offend in ſaying ſo) I could be eaſily content the Plot it ſelf ſhould convince you, ſince my words are ſo lightly regarded; but now every where Danger ſurrounds us, <hi>Catiline</hi> dares us with his Army, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecret and unknown Enemies within our own Walls, in the Boſom of our own City, ready for an Inſurrection; neither can all the Preparations we can make, nor all our private Councils imaginable, be too ſoon put in practice to prevent it.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60603:54"/> Wherefore my Sentence is, that ſince the Nefarious Plots and Aſſociations of ſome wicked and deſperate Citizens, threaten ſo imminent a Danger to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the Conſpirators convicted by the Evidence of <hi>Vulturtius</hi> and the <hi>Allobroges,</hi> and by their own Confeſſions have deſign'd both us and <hi>Rome</hi> for Blood, and Fire, and other unparallel'd Cruelties, 'tis neceſſary, by the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our own Fore-fathers, they ſhould ſuffer condign Puniſhment, as men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of Capital Offences.</p>
            <p>Soon as <hi>Cato</hi> had ended, all the <hi>Conſular Order,</hi> and moſt of the <hi>Senate</hi> approved his Sentence, and mightily applauded the bravery of his Courage, branding others with the name of Coward, that ſeem'd to oppoſe it, and accordingly paſs'd a Decree for their Execution. As ſoon as the Senate broke up, the <hi>Conſul,</hi> thinking it beſt to take the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of the approaching night, gave Orders to the <hi>Triumviri</hi> to make every thing ready for that purpoſe; according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60603:54"/> after he had diſpoſed his Guards, he conducts <hi>Lentulus</hi> to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic dict. à Coercendo,</hi> from reſtraining Men of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: it had two principal Parts, one called <hi>Tullianum,</hi> (into which <hi>Lentulus</hi> was caſt) and the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur:</hi> theſe two Places were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for Execution; in the <hi>Tullianum</hi> they only ſtrangl'd Malefactors; it had its name from <hi>Serv. Tullius,</hi> a Roman King, who firſt invented it.</note> 
               <hi>Carcer,</hi> the reſt of the Conſpirators were brought in by the <hi>Praetors.</hi> There is a place in the <hi>Carcer</hi> called the <hi>Tullianum,</hi> a little on the left hand, about twelve Foot deep, fortify'd on every ſide with Walls, and over it a Chamber built with ſtone Arches; but exceeding dark, ſtinking, and of a very horrid Aſpect. As ſoon as <hi>Lentulus</hi> was let down into this Place, he was ſtrangl'd. Thus that great <hi>Patrician</hi> of the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Family of the <hi>Cornelii,</hi> who had been honour'd with the <hi>Conſular Dignity,</hi> met a Fate every way juſt and equal to the blackneſs of his Treaſons. <hi>Cethegus, Statilius, Gabinius,</hi> and <hi>Ceparius,</hi> took their leave of Life in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were thus doing at <hi>Rome, Catiline,</hi> out of the Forces he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60603:55"/> brought with him and thoſe which <hi>Manlius</hi> led, muſter'd two<note n="*" place="margin">So called <hi>à Deligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi> An ordinary Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion conſiſted of ten Cohorts, containing three Maniples, each Maniple two Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. So that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of ſixty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men.</note> Legions, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up his Troops, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of his Souldiers, when at firſt his whole Army conſiſted but of two thouſand; but of all his Forces, only one fourth part was well diſciplin'd and arm'd; the reſt only carried ſmall Darts, Lances, and other ſharp Clubs, Armour only of Fortune and Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>But as ſoon as <hi>Antonius</hi> began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with his Army, <hi>Catiline</hi> took his march over the Mountains, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to remove his Camp, either to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the City or <hi>Gallia,</hi> and ſo to give no opportunity of Battel at all to the adverſe Armies; for he hop'd in a ſhort time to have the Number of his Forces much augmented, if his Confederates at <hi>Rome</hi> had but begun the attempt: therefore he refuſed the Services of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60603:55"/> thoſe of whom at firſt he might have had a conſiderable Force; and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Strength and Aids of the Conſpirators at home, he thought it then, beneath the Honour of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> to communicate it to every Slave and Fugitive.</p>
            <p>But when News was brought him, at the Camp, that the whole Plot was diſcovered at <hi>Rome,</hi> and condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment inflicted on <hi>Lentulus, Cethegus,</hi> and the reſt, and that moſt of them, whom the hopes of Plunder and the deſire of <hi>Reformation</hi> had inclin'd to War, were now fall'n off, he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately remov'd by great Marches over the rough Mountains into the <hi>Piſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Territories,</hi> deſigning by by-ways ſecretly to fly into <hi>Gallia.</hi> But Q <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellus Celer,</hi> commanded three Legions at <hi>Picaenum,</hi> and imagin'd by reaſon of the Straits <hi>Catiline</hi> was in, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned ſome ſuch thing; therefore when the Scouts had given him notice
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60603:56"/> of his March, he ſeaſonably remov'd his Tents, and encamped at the foot of the Mountains, on purpoſe to ſtop his Paſſage into <hi>Gallia.</hi> Neither was <hi>Antonius,</hi> with his Army far off, in the ſmooth and level Ground, that he might the better purſue the flight of <hi>Cataline;</hi> who when he ſaw himſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viron'd with the Mountains, and the number of his Enemies, that in the City all his Undertakings went croſs and retrograde, and that there were no hopes of Flight or Safety, he thought beſt in ſuch an Extremity to try the fortune of a War; and therefore reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to engage <hi>Antonius</hi> as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Calling a Counſel of War, he thus beſpoke them.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sic Saluſtius in Jugurtha. Plura dicerem ſi timidis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem verba adderent, nam ſtrenais abande dictum puto. Et demoſth. in Oratione, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>I know by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, Souldiers, that the greateſt force of Words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to provoke
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60603:56"/> Valour, nor can any Army of weak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtrong; or of Cowards, valiant, by the inſinuating Eloquence of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals Oration; for every Breaſt whom Nature hath endued with manly Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and a warlike Propenſity, ſhould endeavour to render it the more ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and illuſtrious in the dangerous Hazards of a juſt War: but him whom neither Glory nor Adverſity can incite to Valour 'tis in vain to perſwade, ſince the force of natural Cowardiſe hinders its Operation But I only call'd you together to adviſe you a few things and make you acquainted with my Deſign; for you all know, Souldiers, what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Calamities the Sloth and Folly of <hi>Lentulus</hi> have brought both upon himſelf and us, inſomuch, that whilſt I expected Auxiliaries from the City my Paſſage into <hi>Gallia</hi> is block'd up. Now indeed, with what an Aſpect our Affairs look you all know as well as I: two Armies of our Enemies attend
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60603:57"/> us; one ſtops our Progreſs for the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the other for <hi>Gallia,</hi> and for us to remain longer here, (tho we had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it) yet the want of Proviſion, and other Neceſſaries, conſtrains us to the contrary; therefore wherever we go, nothing but the Sword muſt force the Paſſage, wherefore I adviſe you to be reſolute and couragious; and ſince we muſt commence the Battel, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that you carry Riches, Glory, and Honour, nay <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, in your right hands. If we conquer they are all ſecure we ſhall have Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions enough, and all the Colonies, and free Towns will lye open to us; but if Fear and Cowardiſe ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, we muſt expect the contrary, for no Place nor Friend will protect him whom Arms will not: beſides, there is a great Difference in the Cauſe of War between us and our Enemies; we fight for our own Country, Lives, and Liberties, they only for the ſuperfluous
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60603:57"/> Power of a few great Men; wherefore that ye may the more couragiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter them, remember that you are <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſet before you the old <hi>Roman</hi> Valour. No one, unleſs a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, will ever exchange War for Peace; and 'tis the greateſt Madneſs imaginable, to hope for Safety by Flight, and turn your Backs upon your Enemies, when they are ſufficiently defended by the Armour you carry. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in fight they that fear moſt are in the greateſt Danger; but Courage is like Walls and Bulwarks. When I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Souldiers, who you are, and reflect on all your former Actions, I have ſufficient hopes that Victory will attend us; your Spirits, Age, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Valour, and which is more, the prevalent force of Neceſſity, which makes Cowards valiant, plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it. But if Fortune is grown en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious of our Valour, fall not unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd, nor be taken, and kill'd like
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60603:58"/> tame Beaſts, but like true Romans dye fighting, and leave a dear, bloody, and a lamentable Victory for your Enemies to boaſt of.</p>
            <p>When he ſpoke this, after a ſhort pauſe, he commanded them to ſound an Alarm, and leads his Forces into a Plain, and then, to inſpire them with the greater Courage, he himſelf mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd them on foot for, according to the ſcituation of the Plain, which was between two Mountains on the left hand, and an huge craggy Rock on the right, he plac'd Eight <hi>Cohorts</hi> in the Front, and the reſt in a more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſs, for a Recruit. In the Rear of theſe, he choſe out the moſt experienc'd <hi>Centurions,</hi> and every the beſt diſciplind and beſt arm'd of the Common Souldiers for the <hi>Forlorn Hope,</hi> and appointed <hi>C. Manlius</hi> to command the Right, and a certain <hi>Faeſulanian</hi> the left wing of the Army, and he himſelf
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60603:58"/> with his <hi>Freemen</hi> and <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> betook themſelves near the<note n="*" place="margin">The Eagle was the common Enſign of the <hi>Romans,</hi> but this was a particular Eagle which <hi>C. Marius</hi> had in his Army in the Cymbrian War.</note> 
               <hi>Eagle.</hi> which <hi>C. Marius</hi> was ſaid to have in the Cymbrian War.</p>
            <p>Of the adverſe Army, <hi>C. Antoninus,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, being ſick of the Gout, was ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd incapable of accompanying it, ſo committed the Charge of it to <hi>M. Petrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who plac'd the <hi>Veteran Cohorts</hi> (which he rais'd in haſte) in the Front, and the reſt of the Army for a Supply in the Rear, and riding round the Body, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them ſeverally by their Names, encourag'd, and intreated them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member they were about to fight againſt unarmed Thieves and Robbers, for no leſs cauſe than their own <hi>Country, Children,</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Petreius</hi> was a man altogether trayn'd up to War, and had diſcharg'd with great honour and credit the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of <hi>Tribune, Praefect, Praetor,</hi> and <hi>Legat.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60603:59"/>
            <p>When they were all prepar'd, and in a fit Poſture, <hi>Petreius</hi> gave the ſignal, and commanded the <hi>Cohorts</hi> to move forwards, <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Army did the ſame, till they approached one another ſo near, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe were <hi>Feren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarii, à ferendo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wear no Armour, Swords, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as others, but only ſlings and ſtones.</note> light harneſs'd Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries, arm'd only with Slings and Stones, could begin the Battel; immediately with a great ſhout and a deadly feud, they ruſh'd on all together, and leaving their Darts, made uſe of no other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons than their Swords. The Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran Souldiers, fir'd with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their former Valour, fought hand to hand very vigorouſly, and met with no leſs vigorous reſiſtance. In the mean time <hi>Catiline</hi> was not idle, but was very often with the light-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs'd Auxiliaries in the Front, helping and incouraging thoſe that fought va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly, bringing in freſh Supplies in the places of the wounded, providing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60603:59"/> and taking care for every thing, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nobly himſelf, and killing many of his <hi>Enemies,</hi> and diſcharg'd at once the duty of a <hi>Valiant Souldier,</hi> and an <hi>excellent Commander. Petreius,</hi> when he ſaw <hi>Catiline</hi> behave himſelf ſo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, and fought with greater reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution than he expected, preſently brought the Praetorian Cohort into the midſt of the Enemy, and made a very great and ſurprizing ſlaughter, and they but very weakly and confuſedly reſiſted him, then made a very fierce and valiant aſſault on both <hi>Wings</hi> of <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Army; in which Conflict <hi>Manlius,</hi> and the <hi>Faeſulanian</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, dy'd fighting. But when <hi>Catiline</hi> ſaw his Forces thus rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and himſelf almoſt totally deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, only a few remaining with him, reflecting on the <hi>Nobility</hi> of his <hi>Family</hi> and his former <hi>Dignity,</hi> ſcorn'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>prey</hi> to his <hi>Foes,</hi> and be taken
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60603:60"/> 
               <hi>tamely,</hi> deſperately ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in among the thickeſt of his Enemies, and was ſlain fighting<note n="*" place="margin">Sic Florus. Pulcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima morte ſi pro Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria ſic cecidiſſet Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina.</note>.</p>
            <p>The Battel done, you might then ſee what reſolute Valour and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Courage poſſeſs'd the minds of <hi>Catiline</hi>'s whole Army, for almoſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, when dead, cover'd with their Carkaſſes the ſame places, where juſt before, when alive, they ſtood fighting; but theſe few, whom the <hi>Praetorian Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort</hi> had ſcatter'd and put to flight, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took of the ſame fate, but the Body of <hi>Catiline</hi> was found at a great diſtance from his own Army, in the midſt of the whole Body of his Enemies, juſt expir'd, and ſeem'd to retain the ſame fierceneſs in his looks when dead, which he had in his mind when living. Laſtly, in both Armies, neither in flight nor fight was there one No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Ingenuous Citizen taken, but on both ſides they valu'd their
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60603:60"/> own Lives at no dearer rate than the Lives of their Enemies. Neither had the Roman Army any reaſon to boaſt they had obtain'd a joyful and advantageous Victory without Bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; for every of the moſt valiant and courageous either dy'd fighting, or was ſeverely wounded, beſides many who came out of the Tents, either out of Curioſity, or for the ſake of Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, tumbling the dead Bodies of the Enemy. One found a Kinſman, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Friend, and ſome their Enemies; ſo, promiſcuouſly over the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Joy and Grief, Gladneſs, and Mourning invaded every one.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60603:61"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>James Norris</hi> at the Kings-Arms without <hi>Temple-Bar. 1683.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>MAſſinello;</hi> Or, A Satyr againſt the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation, and the <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Riot. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eromena:</hi> Or, The Noble Sranger. A <hi>Novel.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Tractatus adverſus Reprobationis Abſoluta Decretum, Nova Methodo &amp; ſuccentiſſimo Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendio adornatus; &amp; in duos libros digeſtus.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p n="4">4. An <hi>Idea</hi> of Happineſs, in a Letter to a Friend, Enquiring wherein the greateſt Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs attainable by Man in this Life does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A Murnival of Knaves, or Whiggiſm plainly Diſplay'd, and (if not grown ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) <hi>Burleſqu'd</hi> out of Countenance, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Haec &amp; Hic;</hi> Or the <hi>Feminine</hi> Gender more worthy than the <hi>Maſculine.</hi> Being a Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of that Ingenious and Innocent Sex from the biting Sarcaſms, bitter Satyrs, and opprobrious Calumnies, wherewith they are dayly (tho undeſervedly) Aſpers'd by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent Tongues and Pens of Malevolent Men. Twelves.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60603:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
